<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Infant-baptisme justified by a nevv discovery and also, several scripture allegories adjusted upon the like account. By William Parker clerk, incumbent of Wrotham in Kent.</title>
            <author>Parker, William, fl. 1651-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 191 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56404</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218672</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830244</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830244</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34694</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56404)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2035:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Infant-baptisme justified by a nevv discovery and also, several scripture allegories adjusted upon the like account. By William Parker clerk, incumbent of Wrotham in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Parker, William, fl. 1651-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63 [i.e. 69], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1 reads: Infant baptism justified by a nevv discovery.</note>
                  <note>Page 69 is misnumbered 63.</note>
                  <note>The final page contains a postscript.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34694:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Infant-Baptiſme JUSTIFIED BY A NEVV DISCOVERY: And alſo, Several Scripture Allegories adjuſted upon the like Account.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM PARKER</hi> Clerk, Incumbent of WROTHAM In KENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author. 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34694:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34694:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS neceſſity brought, and brings forth the inveſtigation of all Arts, (eſpecially Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick) and perfects them; So a kind of neceſſity puts us upon this attempt, which we offer unto thee in reference to <hi>Infant-Baptiſm;</hi> otherwiſe we had not put <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ad tabulant,</hi> to declare what we have offered on Gods behalf for his allowance of the practice of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> upon the accounts reſpectively, betwixt it and <hi>Circumciſion</hi> in general, and betwixt <hi>Infant-Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> in ſpecial, to be conſidered in their Adminiſtrations reſpectively.</p>
            <p>The ſaid neceſſity is, for that we have been ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized, and impleaded at Law for Printing (as it's fained) in a certain Book called <hi>The late Aſſembly of Divines Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith examined concerning</hi> Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Where there is nothing, we do appeal to all intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and unbyaſſed by-ſtanders to give evidence againſt us, if there be any thing Printed againſt it in the ſaid Book, when it's examined what we have replyed to a certain Section in their Chapter of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which they have there laid down and declared.</p>
            <p>Their aſſertion in the fourth Section of the ſaid Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is, <hi>That not only thoſe that do actually profeſs Faith in, and Obedience to Christ; but alſo the Infants of one or both believing Parents,</hi> (for ſo they order it) <hi>are to be Baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To that aforeſaid we have replyed, and tell them, that the ſaid aſſertion (ſo diſpoſed in order, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially laid down as it is) we ſay it's too far dipt in errour; the reaſon why we uſe the ſaid expreſs <hi>(Dipt)</hi> is,
<pb facs="tcp:34694:3"/>for that it's an alluſion to their own expreſs <hi>Dipt, Sect.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>And truly there, their fourth aſſertion is Dipt in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour upon a twofold account; one the leſſer, (yet an errour) the other the greater, which they are guilty of; the leſſer is the point of Order and Method; For they ſay the Infants of one, or both believing Parents are to be Baptized, which is <hi>à dictum fruſtra,</hi> and immetho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical; For if it be true, that Infants of one believing Parent are to be Baptized, then much more of both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents muſt be in rationality underſtood to be Baptized; Therefore to lay down <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents in that Order aforeſaid, is <hi>immethodicè dictum;</hi> For it's an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, againſt method; for if one of Believing Parents, then much more of both ought to be Baptized.</p>
            <p>This aforeſaid we do but hint, for that it's but a Criticiſm from our obſervation, though <hi>re verâ,</hi> true, againſt Order and Method, as it is diſpoſed by them in their ſaid aſſertion.</p>
            <p>And as for their further aſſerting that Infants are to be Baptized, but not ſo much as taking notice, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing in what reſpect Infants of believing Parents are to be Baptized, is a great failing <hi>in defectu ex omiſſione,</hi> for that there are two modes or reſpects to be conſidered in Baptizing Infants. One is, as it's expreſsly comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Scripture to Baptize Infants. The other, as it is not forbidden in Scripture.</p>
            <p>Both theſe reſpects aforeſaid, ought to have been conſidered by them and declared, whether they do mean as it's commanded expreſsly in Scripture (or as it's not expreſsly forbidden) to Baptize Infants.</p>
            <p>Now for them to impoſe, as they do in their ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:34694:3"/>aſſertion, a kind of neceſſity of Baptizing Infants; ſaying, <hi>Infanss of ſuch and ſuch, are to be Baptized,</hi> and not declaring in what reſpect they are to be Baptized, either as commanded, or not forbidden. This may occaſion much errour, for that it may make many to miſtake their meaning upon the account aforeſaid, in reference unto the two ſaid reſpective modes or manners of Baptizing Infants.</p>
            <p>For who can tell, (but themſelves) ſince they deelare it not in what of the two modes they intend their ſaid aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be taken, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that Infants are to be Baptized</p>
            <p>Hence we come with our Reply, and ſay, their ſaid aſſertion is two far Dipt in errour, being too looſly and too generally laid down by them, in that they name not the mode or manner how, or in what reſpect Infants are to be Baptized, for that (as we reply) Infants are no where in expreſs tearms commanded to be Baptized.</p>
            <p>Yet they may (as we preſently after ſay) be Baptized, for that <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is no where forbidden; and alſo for that their being Baptized may be to as good purpoſe (as we ſhall by and by demonſtrate) to others at preſent, and to themſelves afterward if occaſion ſerve, as ever <hi>Infant-Circumciſion</hi> was adminiſtred for.</p>
            <p>So that it appears, that what we have there replyed unto their ſaid aſſertion, is, and muſt be comprehended in a compound diſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et axiom, which contains the <hi>totum integrale</hi> of what we have ſaid, conſtituted in two diſtinct modes, manners or reſpects, in and upon which Infants are not to be, or may be Baptized.</p>
            <p>And further, we ſay in reference to their 5. <hi>Section,</hi> that to deny <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> in the Countreys and places where the Chriſtian Magiſtrates require and command
<pb facs="tcp:34694:4"/>it to be done, there to deny it (we ſay) is a Sin of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy againſt thoſe Magiſtrates, for that obedience to Magiſtrates is abſolutely commanded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm</hi> is no where forbidden, and for that it may be done upon ſo good an account, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>From all aforeſaid, the intelligent and impartial by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtander may obſerve <hi>ſimplici &amp; uno intuitu,</hi> that we have not Printed <hi>omnino,</hi> altogether againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> but only againſt one mode or manner of Baptizing Infants, as not commanded in expreſs Scripture, but owned in the other mode as it's not forbidden.</p>
            <p>Hence if our accuſers had had ſo much diſcretion in them, as to diſtinguiſh of a diſcreet axiom, in which all that we have ſaid in reference to <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> is diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and laid down as aforeſaid, they would have bluſht to have impleaded us to Print, eſpecially altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> for that a diſcreet axiom conſiſts always of a negative and affirmative, or affirmative and negative, wherein it's diſpoſed, at leaſt it always conſiſts of two diſſentany or diſagreeing parts, in which one of them only is true, the other is not; as for inſtance, <hi>Nabal</hi> was a rich man, but a Fool; <hi>Abraham</hi> was a rich Man, yet a wiſe Man.</p>
            <p>Where we ſee in thoſe two inſtances two differing parts reſpectively, both parts diſagreeing reſpectively in each, as rich, but differing in both other parts reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, in reference to wiſdom and folly; <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a rich Man, and Wiſe; But <hi>Nabal</hi> a rich Man, yet a Fool; but they might have been reſpectively one like the other in Riches and Wiſdom, and in Riches and Folly, for that both are contingent and not neceſſary axioms, becauſe they might have been otherwiſe then
<pb facs="tcp:34694:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are. Hence ſuch axioms are called diſcreet axioms, differing only in ſome Logical reſpects in their parts and not otherwiſe; and therefore might have been agreers in their axiomatical diſpoſitions reſpectively; So might the ſaid Aſſembly have declared their ſaid aſſertion, <hi>That Infants are to be Baptized</hi> in a diſcreet axiom; ſaying, <hi>Infants are to be Baptiſed,</hi> yet not as commanded expreſsly in Holy Writ, but as not forbidden; which if they had ſo diſpoſed the ſaid aſſertion, we had been <hi>ejuſdem animi</hi> with them, and not have told them that their ſaid aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (or mode of ſo declaring it in a diſcreet axom) was too far Dipt in errour.</p>
            <p>In which we declare our Reply againſt their aſſertion, ſaying, <hi>Infants are no where commanded in Scripture to be Baptized, notwithſtanding they may be Baptized, becauſe it is no where in Scripture forbidden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the truth, and the whole truth, and nothing but the truth in what we have Printed in the ſaid Book concerning <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence we ſay, that if our accuſers aforeſaid had had ſo much diſcretion in them; as to have underſtood a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret axiom, they would not (for ſhame) have impleded us at Law, for Printing againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if they think we impoſe too much ignorance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them by our reflection aforeſaid, then t'will appear, that what they have impleaded us for, was, and is out of the malitious and ſelf deſign, to wreſt from us, as they have kept us out, ever ſince <hi>July</hi> 1662. of our Eceleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Living, the Vicarage of <hi>Wrotham</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi> They tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing and charging us alſo upon all occaſions (when we implead our defence) to have Printed againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm;</hi> and ſcandalizing us many ways beſides, as not
<pb facs="tcp:34694:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be in Holy Orders, when we are 64 years of age, and were Incumbent in two Livings ſucceſſively in <hi>Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> long ſince, as it is well known; and therefore it's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely upon the account aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>But the truth is, they are loſt by reaſon of a Miniſter's death in <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> with whom they were left in the time of the ſad War in 1643, who dyed a long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we knew of it, and left his Eſtate to a <hi>Scotch-man</hi> his Kinſman, who carryed all the ſaid Miniſter left him away into <hi>Scotland,</hi> or ſo diſpoſed of Papers otherwiſe, that we could never find them, or hear of them. And upon this account, our accuſers do preſs us to ſhew our Orders. But whether it be becauſe our Accuſer ſhews ſufficiently his Diſorders we ſay not. But that is the one of the two <hi>impedimenta obſtantia,</hi> which are proſecuted againſt us; but if they charge us with one crime of immorality, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, or unreaſonableneſs committed by us in the ſaid place, and prove it againſt us for above 20 years, wherein we have lived amongſt them, we'l yield our cauſe unto them; and as for <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> we have conſtantly (it's well known) practiſed it in, and at <hi>Wrotham</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quis niſi mentis inops contra ſua practica ſcribit,</l>
               <l>Certè eſt illius tutior unda fide?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who but a brainſick, bereav'd of's wits,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prints, Preaches, what his practice contradicts?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His credit ſure is more unſtable</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Than</hi> Stygian <hi>water in the Fable,</hi> We ſay no more.</l>
               <l>Quicquid ex merito venit, patiamur ferendum eſt,</l>
               <l>Quae venit indigne paena dolenda venit.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>What is from undeſert purſude as crime,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Doth well deſerve to be complain'd in Rhime.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM PARKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34694:5"/>
            <head>Infant Baptiſm Juſtified by A NEVV DISCOVERY.</head>
            <head type="sub">Exitus acta probabit.</head>
            <p>NOW to make way to the demonſtration of the ſaid <hi>New Diſcovery,</hi> in reference to the Juſtification of <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi> We think it not amiſs to re-mind the Reader, that ſuch was the Lords love of pity and compaſſion to the diſobedient fallen Man-kind, that he was willing to reſtore Man-kind to a new and innocent life again; that ſo he might have fellowſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion again with his God, and enjoy the Beatifical Viſion of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent, Bliſs, and Happineſs, in the Kingdom of Heaven. <hi>John</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <p>Which ſaid New Life and State, (the Introduction to the ſaid Tranſcendent Bliſs) Our Saviour exemplifies by a Child-like inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent life, and ſtate; therefore he ſet (upon occaſion) a little Child in the midſt of his Diſciples; and ſaid, <hi>Except you be Converted, and become as a little Child, ye cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. Mat.</hi> 18.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34694:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Hence it's evident, that a Child-like Innocent life and ſtate, is made (by Our Saviour) the Pattern and Exemplar of the ſaid New Heavenly Life and State.</p>
            <p>Now ſince Man-kind was by Diſobedience, (and ſtill will be be through Diſobedience) fallen, as aforeſaid, from the ſaid Innocent Life, and muſt of neceſſity come to it again, before he be fit to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven; there muſt be the removing of all impediments that hinder the attainment to Bliſs; which ſaid impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments, are the Sins and Tranſgreſſions, which ſtand in oppoſition to Innocency, and ſeparate betwixt Us, and Our God. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Lord in his Infinit Wiſdom and Goodneſs, Ordained two moſt ſignificant and fit Sacraments, to Figure forth in their Myſteries, the way and means whereby the Tranſgreſſions and Sins may be removed, and taken away from the depraved heart of the repenting Sinner.</p>
            <p>Which two Sacraments are <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The one, <hi>(viz.) Circumciſion,</hi> to cut off and deſtroy the groſs Sins, which muſt firſt be removed (as we are commanded, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. <hi>to caſt away our groſs Sins</hi>) and then the waſhing away all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining defilements in the depraved heart of Man-kind, for that <hi>no unclean thing ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. Rev.</hi> 21.21.27.</p>
            <p>Hence the Lord ſaith, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.27. <hi>Come out from among them, and touch no unclean thing, and I will be your God; and you ſhall be my People:</hi> Therefore the Lord in his like Infinite Wiſdom and Goodneſs, brought in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> upon the account aforeſaid; as appears <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26, 27. where it's ſaid Chriſt gave himſelf, <hi>that he might Sanctify and cleanſe his Church,</hi> &amp;c. by the waſhing of <hi>water</hi> in and through the word, that he might preſent it to himſelf a moſt Glorious <hi>Church, not having ſpot, or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing; but that it might be Holy, and without blemiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee how and wherefore <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alſo was brought in after <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> to be adminiſtred: and theſe two Sacraments are ſo eſſentially relating and depending on each other reſpectively; as one cannot be compleat in its operation and Myſterie without the other; For if the groſs Sins be not taken away, how can remaining defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sin be purged away? and if remaining defilements be not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34694:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo purged away, there can be no coming to the Innocent life again, and ſo no entrance into the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>For no unclean thing ſhall enter into the ſaid Kingdom, Revel.</hi> 21. So that we ſee the ſaid uſe, and eſſential dependency as aforeſaid, on each other reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in reference to the ſame end. And <hi>Circumciſion</hi> muſt have its firſt work alſo, upon the account aforeſaid; and therefore we muſt firſt begin with <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and we ſhall lay it down as it is in its fitneſs for the end aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The neceſſity of its application in its Myſterie for the ſaid end.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Lay down the Perſons who firſt received <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the Perſons who were in the firſt diſpenſation always to be Circumciſed.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, offer to Conſideration, whether it be not to be granted, that the then Circumciſed were then particularly and intentionally to be Baptiſed in reference to the removing of all Sin? for that the natural dependency betwixt them, as aforeſaid, is ſo nearly and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially annexed together, as aforeſaid; that one cannot be efficacious and uſeful without the other: and that therefore none of Us can have fellowſhip with the Lord, without the operation of them both reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively; and therefore it's ſaid, that <hi>Abraham</hi> received the Sign of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> as the Seal of the Rightouſneſs of the Faith he had in his <hi>Uncircumciſion;</hi> whence it is evident he had the Inward and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> before he had the outward; and had Spiritual <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alſo, for that he had in his Uncircumciſion, ſaith the Text, before he was outwardly Circumciſed, the Rightouſneſs of Faith, which <hi>purifies the Heart, Acts</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>Now Faith is annexed to the Ordinance of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſaith OUr Saviour, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. and <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Abraham</hi> recieved alſo (as aforeſaid) Spiritual <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> in his <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> and therefore We believe that Spiritual <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> and Spiritual <hi>Baptiſm</hi> were to be received, and intended to be ſo together, though but the outward Diſpenſation of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was appointed only at firſt to be in practice: Yet that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was indeed intended in its Spiritual uſe alſo, appears by that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2. <hi>Moreover Brethren, I would not that ye ſhould be ignorant how that our Fathers were all under the Cloud: and all paſsed through the red Sea: and were all Baptiſed unto</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Cloud, and in the Sea;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34694:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>where it's apparent, they were all Prophetically Baptiſed with the Ceremony of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alſo, who were but practically Circumciſed only, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence where one of the ſaid Ordinances are outwardly by Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation appointed of right, and by Gods appointment, the other alſo is, and muſt interpretatively (as aforeſaid) be underſtood to belong; and therefore it will infer alſo <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> to be juſt, and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able upon the account of Gods appointing <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Infants to be Circumciſed in truth; But we leave it to be ſeriouſly thought on, and conſidered, and argue it at preſent no farther on that account; but paſs on to ſet forth <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> according as before hinted.</p>
            <p>And firſt, unto its fitneſs for the end and purpoſe it was ordained for, which will appear in the ſignification of the word it ſelf, (<hi>viz.</hi>) <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> which is derived from the Latine word <hi>Circumſcindere,</hi> to cut about; and anſwers to the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the Apoſtle uſes to expreſs <hi>Circumciſion</hi> by, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.15. which ſignifies to cut about, and ſo to cut off; and anſwers alſo to the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. which <hi>Arius Montanus</hi> renders, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidit,</hi> to cut off together, which is a moſt apt rendring of the ſaid word, according to its innate ſignification and ſcope, for which it is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, even to figure forth in a Myſterie (by being applied to and on the fore-skin of the Fleſh) the cutting off the ſtrong Luſts from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved heart of the diſobedient humanity, which will be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways deſtroyed, then the Sons of <hi>Anack</hi> could be deſtroyed in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> by cutting them off, which were, (as a Divinely Spirited <hi>Germane</hi> ſaith) the Figure of theſe ſtrong and powerful Luſts: which unbelieving Chriſtians ſay, (becauſe they know not, nor make uſe of the Spiritual <hi>Circumciſion</hi> aforeſaid) can never be ſubdued in this life: even as the unbelieving <hi>Iſraelites</hi> aforetime cryed out they could never be able to overcome thoſe Giants, the Sons of <hi>Anack.</hi> Therefore the Lord of neceſſity brought in <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> to Figure forth in its Myſterie the way and means, whereby the ſaid ſtrong and Giant-like Luſts (ſo powerful through cuſtom and habit) ſhould be deſtroyed, in order to the coming to the ſaid Innocent Life and State. Which ſaid <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> the Lord annexed to his Law of Compulſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24. that is, (as We believe) until Chriſt come to perform his Office on thoſe who were Diſciplined
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34694:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>under the ſaid Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10, 13. And made fit thereby for that his Office to be performed in them by Him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.45.</p>
            <p>Now the ſaid <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was adjoined to the ſaid Law; for that the ſaid Law was appointed by the Lord, to reſtrain the abominable nature of Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.1. 2. To diſcover alſo the Curſe due to the Sin; from both which diſcoveries, when they are ſet home by his Spirit on the Heart. Then there doth, and muſt, (<hi>Ex vi antecedentium</hi>) ariſe a fear and trembling in the Sinner, as appears by St. <hi>Paul's</hi> expreſs, <hi>Rom</hi> 7.24. <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. So <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.29. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.20, 21. Upon which work, the Sinner is willing to part with any thing, in reference to his Salvation, as <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.16. it's ſaid upon the like occaſion, <hi>They put away their ſtrange gods, and ſerved the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence alſo, the Fear is ſaid to be <hi>the beginning of wiſdom, Pſal.</hi> 111.10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.10. it's ſaid <hi>the wiſe man Fears, and departs from Evil;</hi> For then we are willing to do any thing to be ſaved, as aforeſaid. Therefore the Lord joyned <hi>Circumciſion</hi> to his Law of Compulſion, which works the ſaid Fear upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence aforeſaid, to make the groſs Sinner willing to be Circumciſed in a Myſterie, that is, to have his groſs Sins cut off, which the Sinner muſt do, or he cannot come to the ſaid Innocent life and ſtate again; to be made fit to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Joſhua</hi> was commanded (before he brought the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Tipe of the Kingdom of Heaven) to <hi>make ſharp knives, and Circumciſe all the males, Joſh.</hi> 5.2, 3. The Original expreſs is, <hi>Make thee</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>cultros petrarum, knives of ſtones,</hi> or rather of <hi>ſharp flints, and Circumciſe the males;</hi> which knives were a fit Figure of the Circumciſing knife of the Law, to which Circumciſion, was annexed for the end aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>For that the Law was by Gods Command written in Stone, which is a Tipe of the Heart of ſtone; ſo made through cuſtom, and obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs in Sin, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.19. wherein the Law, when the Heart becomes a Heart of Fleſh again, is to be written.</p>
            <p>Now that the Laws were written in Stone, it appears <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.1.</p>
            <p>The Perſons who were firſt Circumciſed by Gods Command,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34694:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>was <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17. who received it after he believed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. And therefore he was then gone beyond Circumciſions work and ſcope, for which <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was appointed, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Abraham</hi> had then no Perſonal need of Circumciſions work, which was appointed to figure forth in a Myſterie, the cutting off the groſs Sins, as aforeſaid: for He had attained (as it appears) to the Rightouſneſs of Faith, which he had in his Uncircumciſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.10. and before his Circumciſion was received, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>Where, by the way we may apprehend, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was then Circumciſed by way of Office only, as to be thereby a repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and document, to hold forth what <hi>Circumciſion</hi> related unto, and aimed at in the cutting off the groſs Sins, as aforeſaid; in order to the coming on to the Rightouſneſs of Faith, by all the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God: So that hence it appears, that thoſe may have a Divine Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony applyed to them who have no need of it at preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor doth perſonally (at preſent) concern themſelves, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, upon the account aforeſaid Circumciſed, when he had no need to be Circumciſed, in reference to his own perſonal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt was both Circumciſed, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. and after Baptiſed; <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. who had no perſonal need at all of either; for that He was a Lamb without ſpot, holy, harmleſs and undefiled, ſeparated from Sinners, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.26. <hi>In whoſe mouth was no guile:</hi> yet was he both Circumciſed, and Baptiſed.</p>
            <p>Hence its moſt apparent, that Chriſt received <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alſo by way of Office only, as repreſentative and documen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to hold forth, that He is the Miniſter of the Spiritual <hi>Circumciſion</hi> of the Heart, according to that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. and alſo the true Adminiſtrator of the Spiritual <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or Waſhing, as the Apoſtle declares Him to be, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Coll.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>Hence it doth undeniably follow, that thoſe may receive <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> reſpectively, in reference to other Myſteries, then their own perſonal concerns at preſent; for that <hi>Abraham</hi> did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and Chriſt both <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alſo, as aforeſaid. And Our Saviour declares Infants to be the Patterns and Exemplars of the Innocent life and ſtate, <hi>Matt.</hi> 18. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> do relate in their applicatory
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34694:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Myſteries, by way of Office and document, reſpectively to Infants, in order to their being the Exemplars of the Innocent life: So that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alſo, were brought in by the Lord in a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, for the taking away of all groſs Sins, and all remaining defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from repenting penitent ſinners; that ſo they may come thereby to the Child-like Innocent life and ſtate again; of which Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our declares Children to be the Patterns and Exemplars of, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. And alſo for that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> are ſo eſſentially depending on each other, that the one cannot have its accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without the other reſpectively: yet are they as (it's confeſt) declared to be ſet forth in two diſtinct Diſpenſations, (<hi>viz.</hi>) <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> under the Law, and in reference thereunto: <hi>Baptiſm</hi> under the Goſpel, and in reference thereunto. But though they be ſo, as aforeſaid, for diſtinct diſcoveries of their reſpective uſes; and how, and upon no other account they are here brought in; and how, and wherein they became uſeful and ſerviceable, by being joined to the Law and Goſpel reſpectively, in their dipſenſation; and are ſo nearly relating to, and eſſentially depending on each other; that they cannot but be incomplere one without the other, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Neither can <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Infants be more concerned in <hi>Circumciſion</hi> to be Circumciſed by way of Office and good document, than Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Infants are concerned in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> to be Baptiſed in Infancy by way of Office, and good document to others; no, not ſo much: for that as Infants are the Exemplars of Innocency, which is only attained unto by a repenting Sinner, in having his groſs Sins cut off firſt by <hi>Circumciſion</hi> in its Myſterie: and then in having all remaining de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements of Sin waſhed away by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in its Myſterie, which is the neareſt and moſt perſpicuous purge for Innocencies introduction.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Baptiſm</hi> ought to be (we ſay) looked upon to have as much power and influence upon Chriſtians Infants, to be adminiſtred to them in Infancy by way of Office, (though it be not literally commanded alſo) as <hi>Circumciſion</hi> had, when adminiſtred to <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> Infants, upon the account aforeſaid; though it was literally commanded, as it was then needful, ſo to be, for that otherwiſe the Myſterie begun in Infant <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> by way of Office and good do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cument only, had not had its riſe and warrant to be known to be Inſtituted by the Lord for the ſame purpoſe; that the Child-like
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34694:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>innocent life and ſtate, ſhould be the end and ſcope of Circumciſions work in a Myſterie, as aforeſaid: But now that being commanded, there needs not a new command for Chriſtians Infants to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; For it may be demonſtrated <hi>à pari,</hi> that Infant Baptiſm holds forth (undeniably) as good, yea greater uſefulneſs to grown Chriſtians, when its adminiſtred to Infants by way of Office and good document, as Infant Circumciſion was, or could be; though Infant Baptiſm be not literally commanded; for a Command ſhews only the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and pleaſure of the Commander in his Authority, not the <hi>rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem formalem</hi> of the thing Commanded, which is only conſidered in the juſtice and equity of the thing to be done, or not to be done; as Infant Circumciſion was commanded thereupon, to be adminiſtred by way of Office, and good document only to others concerns, not their own at preſent; for Infants were not then apprehenſive and capable of any duty in reference to their then perſonal <hi>Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence may alſo Chriſtians Infants be warrantably Baptiſed, by way of Office, and good document to others; not then to their own Perſonal concerns: though <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> be not commanded lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; (which indeed need not) for that the <hi>ratio formalis</hi> of <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> (which is its fitneſs, and equity to be done, by way of Office and good document,) is in reference to others, not then their own perſonal concerns, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>All this is offered to conſideration occaſionally, as it falls in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentially from ſomething proceeding from Circumciſions diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as aforeſaid. We return to inſiſt further on <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing all his Family by Gods Command, which were born in his Hourſe, or bought with Money, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.13, 27. Where every Male at Eight days old was to be Circumciſed, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. There is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of any further iground of their being Circumciſed; than that they were of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Family.</p>
            <p>Hence it's more then probable, upon the like account, that when <hi>Lidia</hi> appeared to be a Believer; we preſume to ſay, that if there were or had been an Infant, or Infants in <hi>Lidias</hi> houſe at that time when <hi>Paul</hi> Baptiſed her and her whole houſhold, he had Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed them alſo: otherwiſe he had not left <hi>Lidias</hi> Houſe ſo good a document and inſtruction, to mind them to go forward, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour after their Child-like innocent life.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34694:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now give me leave to ſay, upon <hi>Abraham</hi>'s practice in Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing all his Family; as well thoſe that were bought with his Money, as born in his houſe: to offer this alſo to conſideration, to them that do (as they ought) allow of <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> which ſcruple to Baptiſe any Children but Believers Children, as they perſwade themſelves they are whom they Baptiſe.</p>
            <p>The queſtion is, whether upon account of <hi>Abraham's</hi> practice aforeſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in Circumciſing all his Family, whether born in his houſe, or bought with his Money; whether it be not lawful to Baptiſe in like manner the Children of a Turk, or like Nation, if Chriſtian People would take care of its education and inſtruction of Baptiſms work in its Myſterie, as they come to riper years: For that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> Circumciſed all Male Children of his Family, though bought with his Money of a ſtranger.</p>
            <p>Therefore, We thought good to offer this to their Conſideration, who though they allow of <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi> yet limit and reſtrain it within the narrow compaſs of Believing Parents, as they perſwade themſelves they are whom they Baptiſe.</p>
            <p>Further, as for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Circumciſing his ſeed; We find he did it at two ſeveral times or ages: for it it is expreſsly ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.25. firſt <hi>Iſhmael, Abraham</hi>'s Son was 13 years of age when he was Circumciſed, and that at the ſame age or years the Jewiſh Doctors accounted them <hi>Filii praecepti;</hi> that is, fit to be inſtructed and taught the Laws of their perſuaſions, in reference to <hi>Abram</hi>'s and <hi>Moſes</hi>'s inſtructions to the Iſraelites of their Children and Houſhold, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.7.</p>
            <p>Hence it's very conſentaneous and agreeable to Piety; that at the ſame age youth ought to be inſtructed by their Parents and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, even to begin to ſhew forth then their true Circumciſing: that is, their cutting off their groſs Sins of life, which youth are grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up into, for want of Diſcipline and Correction.</p>
            <p>But too many pretending Chriſtians in our days, do omit and neglect it; putting it off, by uſing a Brutiſh Proverb, that <hi>a rugged Colt makes a good Horſe:</hi> as if they could tame (when they pleaſe) their bruitiſhly bred Children, as their rugged Colts are tamed; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Heathens, (commonly ſo called,) could ſay, that Children left ſome time to their Luſts, are hardly reſtrained, <hi>quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſemel eſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34694:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>imbuta recens ſervabit odorem teſta diu;</hi> and Divine Writ tells us, that Youth corrupted, is not eaſily nor frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced again; but it becomes in little time to be like the Sons of <hi>Anack,</hi> ſo ſtrong in Luſts, that they muſt be cut off before they can be ſubdued; and therefore as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>They</hi> (too often) <hi>are ready to l'e down with the Sins of their Youth,</hi> for want of the true Circumciſion, which is the ſpiritual Circumciſion, at <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s age; to ſhew themſelves thereby of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Belief, the Father of the Faithful, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. So that all Parents and Governours, ſhould, when their Children be come to be of <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s age, endeavour to bring them to the Miniſter of the true <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Rom</hi> 15.8. to be Spiritually Circumciſed, in order to their Spiritual <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> that ſo thereby they may attain to the Child-like innocent life and ſtate; to be made capable (as Our Saviour ſaith) <hi>to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was Circumciſed, when <hi>Abraham,</hi> with all his Houſhould were Circumciſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; it is evident, that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was then perſonally a member of the Houſhould of Faith, no repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate at preſent: therefore that which is ſpoken to <hi>Abraham</hi> by the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.11, 12. was only ſpoken in reference to <hi>Sarah</hi> her words, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. and in reference to a higher Myſterie, which is declared by the Apoſtle more fully, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30. (<hi>viz.</hi>) <hi>Caſt out the Bond Woman, and her Son,</hi> which was <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> it was ſpoken of <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s rejection by way of office, as he was born of <hi>Hagar</hi> the Bond Woman, the repreſentative of the Legal Seed of Legal Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantſhip under the Law of Compulſion, and was not to have that Inheritance of the Spiritual Promiſes; which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Sarah</hi> and her Offspring, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.19. <hi>Sarah</hi> which was the Free Woman, the Tipe of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Mother of all true Believers, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26. For it is ſaid to <hi>Abraham. Gen.</hi> 17.20. concerning <hi>Iſhmael, I have bleſſed him, and will make him fruitful: and will mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ply him exceedingly;</hi> which are all ſignals of the Lords good will to <hi>Iſhmael:</hi> And therefore, ſince he was Circumciſed with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> at the ſame time, and had the ſaid Promiſes made to him; ſurely it cannot be that he was perſonally a reprobate at the time of his Birth; for that <hi>Signum</hi> muſt relate to the <hi>Signatum,</hi> which was the perſonal intereſt in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Belief, and houſhold of Faith,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34694:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>by being Circumciſed, and had the Promiſes aforeſaid; For that <hi>relata,</hi> do <hi>ex mutuo conſtare;</hi> that is, give reſpectively being, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtency to each other: therefore <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> uno relato ponitur Correlatum;</hi> that is, one <hi>Relat</hi> being declared, the <hi>Correlat</hi> thereof muſt neceſſarily be inferred, becauſe they do <hi>ex mutuo conſtare,</hi> that is, ariſe mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, as cauſe and effect out of each other: as Fatherhood ariſeth out of Sonhood: if there were no Son, there could be no Father: and if no Father, there could be no Son; therefore they ariſe mutually out of each other: ſo in reference to <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> as aforeſaid; ſince he was Circumciſed, and that by <hi>Abraham</hi> upon Gods Command, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. it muſt follow, that he was perſonally then a member of the houſhold of the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and no reprobate; but only by way of office was he caſt out, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.10. and what he did, was only by way of office, as a repreſentative of what the earthly legal ſeed of the Bond Woman doth to the Seed of Faith; even as the legal Scribes and Phariſees did to Chriſt and his Diſciples; even reject Him and Them, and ſcoff at them, as it is expreſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.29. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.18. <hi>What will this babbler ſay? Acts</hi> 17.18.</p>
            <p>Yet this legal bond offspring of the <hi>Jews</hi> aforeſaid, though they did reject the Chriſt of God Our Saviour, did expect to be Heirs to <hi>Abraham, John</hi> 8.33. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8.</p>
            <p>And ſo much of the firſt Age, or different time of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing his Seed of one of the firſt Ages; or different times of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Circumciſing his Seed, as of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> his Son by <hi>Hagar,</hi> and of his ingraffing by Circumciſion at preſent into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, or houſhold of Faith; and likewiſe of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> his rejecton or caſting out from being Heir with <hi>Sarah</hi> her Seed to the inheritance by Faith, which was done by way of office, as he did bear the Image and repreſentation of the Bond Womans Seed, which was the Seed of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as the <hi>Dutch</hi> call it; that is the Law of Compulſion, that compels us to ſeek a freedom by <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith.</p>
            <p>We come now to ſet forth the other age, or time of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Circumciſing his Seed, and ſo of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> after him; which was at 8 days old, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12. and every Male Child only was to be Circumciſed by the Lords Command at that age, no ſooner or later. 2. The Male Infant that was not then Circumciſed, was to be cut off from the Congregration of <hi>Iſrael, ver.</hi> 14. which was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34694:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>durus ſermo,</hi> a hard ſaying, in reference to Infants at 8. days old, if it was not intended (as it was) by way of off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce, and as a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative of a further and higher Myſterie than the Infant concerns at preſent, for that Infants then were not capable of performing, (no not apprehenſive) of any duty that related to Circumciſions ſcope in its Myſterie aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> of the Male only. 2. At 8. days old only; and if at that age it was not then Circumciſed, it was to be cut off from the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence we ſee, that all the aforeſaid reſpects to be oſerved by <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Male Infants, in reference to their Circumciſion in Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, was not at preſent for their own perſonal concerns; but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rence to higher and further Myſteries to be reprerented thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Male only was to be Circumciſed, for that in the Male is the Manly nature which figureth forth the ſtrength of the humanity, which the Lord calls for to be dedicated to Him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.28 <hi>Thy God hath commanded thy ſtrength.</hi> Therefore the Mother of King <hi>Lemuel,</hi> (i.e. <hi>cum quo eſt Deus,</hi> with whom is God) ſaid to him, <hi>Give not thy ſtrength to Women, Prov.</hi> 31.3. and it's ſaid, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.29. <hi>The glory of young Men is their ſtrength.</hi> Hence, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.14. <hi>I write to you young Men, becauſe ye are ſtrong, and the word of God abideth in you: and you have overcome the wicked one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it was, (we believe) that after the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> came out of <hi>Egypt, the ſtraitneſs and bondage,</hi> (which figured out the ſlavery under the Sin) the Lord commanded all the Males (from 20 years old and upward) ſhould be numbred by their pole, <hi>Num.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. and no Female, nor Children were to be numbred with them.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the Five Thouſand miraculouſly fed with 5 Loaves, and 2 Fiſhes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.22. and of thoſe fed in like manner miraculouſly <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.36, 37. no Women or Children, (though fed with them at the ſame time) were numbred; whoſe reſpective enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (if they had been mentioned) had greatned much the Miracles aforeſaid; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo it's now more than probable, that the Males at 20 years old and upward, were appointed only to be numbred, <hi>Num.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>For that the Males, in whom is the ſtrength of the Humanity which God calls for, were moſt fit for war, in which the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34694:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>to exerciſe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (<hi>Judg.</hi> 1.2.) in a Myſterie, as the ſaid War figured forth to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> the Spiritual Warfar againſt Sin and Satan, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12, 13. <hi>That ſo his Name might become great in</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.1. and they renowned for it, according to their name derived from the name <hi>Iſrael</hi> given to <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he had prevailed with the Angel. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28.</p>
            <p>To which War the Spiritual ſtrength is requiſite; Therefore the Apoſtle exhorts the <hi>Epheſians, Chap.</hi> 6.10, 11. <hi>to be ſtrong in the Lord;</hi> which we may gueſs to be the reaſon that the Lord calls for the ſtrength to be given to him, aforeſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.28.</p>
            <p>Now for that the weakneſs was figured forth in the Female; Therefore the Lord appointed no Sacrament, or Myſterie to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred unto them, which ſurely the Lord would have done, if Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion to Males had been a Sacrament or Myſterie for Infants perſonal priviledges and benefits; for that there is no reſpect of perſons with God: and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. <hi>There is neither Male nor Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, but all are one in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Hence the weakneſs was alſo by way of office held forth in the Female as the ſtrength was figured forth in the Male by way of office.</p>
            <p>And therefore the curſe is threatned to him who hath a Male in his Flock, and offereth to the Lord a corrupt thing, which is (no doubt) the Female: which figured forth the weakneſs, that is contradiſtiact to the ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſon of the ſaid Curſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Female (under the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt thing) was, for that the weakneſs cannot ſubdue and deſtroy the ſtrong Luſts; But the manly Nature, which figureth the ſtrength, muſt do that when it's Circumciſed in a Myſterie; that is, hath its groſs Sins cut off from it; which if they be not, then the Male or manly Nature is weak like the Women.</p>
            <p>Hence it is ſaid to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when captiv'd to their ſtrong Luſts, <hi>How weak is thy heart ſince thou doſt all theſe things, even the work of a preſumptuous whoriſh Woman? Ezek.</hi> 16.30. And it is threatned to them, (<hi>Iſai.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Nah.</hi> 3.13, 10.) who were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved to their Luſts, that Women, yea Children ſhould rule over them, becauſe they were through vitiouſneſs become weak, like Women in paſſions, and like Children in underſtanding and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34694:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34694:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:34694:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And therefore the Lord commanded the Male only to be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed by the Circumciſing knife of the Law, and that in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy or beginning of the fallen Mans ſtate and condition, before the Luſts are grown too ſtrong in him, like the Sons of <hi>Anack,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>Again, the Circumciſing Male was to be on the Eighth day after his birth preciſely, no ſooner, nor later; therefore a great Myſtery was intended, for that many Infants might die before the Fourth, yea, the Second day; which Myſterie is in reference to Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, whoſe day that is, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> us to the true reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. and therefore his day, and it was his day wherein he was Circumciſed, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. who is called the Miniſter of the true Circumciſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8.</p>
            <p>Hence they were Circumciſed on that day, in reference to Chriſt, who is yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.8.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is ſaid, that the Male which was not Circumciſed on that day, was to be cut off from the Congregation of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Which figureth forth (we doubt not) but that thoſe who were not ſpiritually Circumciſed from their groſs Sins, upon and in Chriſts day, that is, by him the Miniſter of the true Circumciſion, muſt be cut off from Chriſts Spiritual Congregation, for ſuch cannot be capable of Baptiſm in its Myſtery, to the waſhing away all remaining defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sin, after the groſs Sins are out off, as aforeſaid; whereby we may have fellowſhip again with Chriſt, and no otherwiſe, as appears 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15, 16. <hi>ver.</hi> 27.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. and therefore Chriſt was alſo Baptiſed himſelf (who needed it not) to figure this forth unto us byway of office alſo. From all aforeſaid declared, concerning <hi>Infant Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing.</hi> 2. Of the Male only. 3. On the Eighth day only; and that if the Male was not then Circumciſed preciſely, no ſooner nor later, that Male ſhould be cut off from the Congregation of the Lord; which was a hard caſe, for that an Infant could not then either further or hinder its Circumciſing: nor is an Infant then either apprehenſive or ſenſible of what was then done to it, by or in its Circumciſion.</p>
            <p>Hence the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Infants were then Circumciſed in reference to others (not their own) perſonal concerns (at preſent,) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were commanded to be Circumciſed by way of office only, and good document to grown <hi>Iſraelites</hi> only at preſent, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>Infant Circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:34694:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>We come now to ſpeak of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> the other neceſſary following Sacrament or Myſterie ordained by the Lord Jeſus, to ſet forth what is further to be done upon and in the true Circumciſed ones, who have their groſs Sins cut off by the Miniſtery of the true <hi>Circumciſion, Rom.</hi> 5.8. and by the true Circumciſing Knife of the Law, which <hi>Joſhuah</hi> in his office made uſe of in a Myſterie, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Baptiſm</hi> we are to ſeek for after we are Circumciſed, even a thorow waſhing away of all remaining deſilements of Sin, which remain in their degrees for ſome time in the Soul, after our groſs Sins are Circumciſed away.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Baptiſm</hi> through waſhing is ſo neceſſary, that without it in its order and degrees performed, we cannot attain to the Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Innocent life and ſtate again, ſet forth by Our Saviour, to be the next way and means of entring into <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven, Mat.</hi> 18. Therefore the Apoſtle exh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rts the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that having theſe Promiſes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.27. <hi>to purge them from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was ordained by the Lord Jeſus for the uſe and end aforeſaid, and muſt follow after Circumciſions uſe and work in its Myſterie is done.</p>
            <p>Hence the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> who came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> (the ſtraits and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage under the ſlavery of Sin, in a Myſterie) were then Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Baptiſed unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the Cloud, and in the Sea, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2.</p>
            <p>So that the Circumciſed ones who came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, were Prophetically Baptiſed alſo unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> which doth clearly hint to us, that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> doth reach (and interpretatively include <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> alſo preſuppoſeth Circumciſions work in its Myſterie.</p>
            <p>Now ſince <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is owned by us to be a Goſpel Ordinance, and ſure alſo thoſe who were Circumciſed, were, as aforeſaid, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically Baptiſed alſo unto <hi>Moſes;</hi> it muſt be granted (obſerve it well) that Chriſt was <hi>Moſes</hi> under the diſpenſation of <hi>Circnmciſion,</hi> for that it is ſaid, <hi>they were Baptiſed unto</hi> Moſes.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is declared to be (<hi>Mat.</hi> 28.) Chriſt's Ordinance, appointed by Him, and performed ſolely by Himſelf, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.27, 28. Hence is Chriſt under the Goſpel diſpenſation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34694:14"/>be looked upon and conſidered to be the true Spiritual Adminiſtrator of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> in its Myſterie; and ſo the Apoſtle calls him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8.</p>
            <p>Now I ſay to you, that Jeſus Chriſt was a Miniſter of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> for the truth of God, to confirm the Promiſes to the Fathers; and that the Gentiles might glorifie God for his mercy, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. and the Apoſtle declares the like, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. <hi>In whom ye alſo were Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with the Circumciſion made without hands, in putting off the body of the Sins of the Fleſh, by the Circumciſion of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence it ſollows from the ſaid expreſſes, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1, 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. that Chriſt was <hi>Moſes</hi> the true <hi>Circumciſor</hi> and <hi>Baptiſor</hi> under the Law, and alſo both of them under the Goſpel alſo; And therefore they are both reſpectively begun and completed in him only, and are to be looked upon as included in each other, like <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Wheels one within the other, <hi>Ezek</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was brought in its office next, to be done after Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſions work is performed in its office and myſterie reſpectively.</p>
            <p>And thence alſo it muſt follow by undeniable conſequence, that if <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> be a good document and inſtruction by way of office, as aforeſaid; ſo is <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> alſo, and muſt be ſo intended by the Lord, and alſo received by us; for that one eſſentially and reciprocally depends upon the other. And here it muſt be granted, that thoſe who were Circumciſed, were declared to be Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Baptiſed in the Cloud, and in the Sea, when they came out of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is evident that ſome little ones were among them who paſſed through the Sea, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.10, 24. Hence they alſo were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in the Cloud, and in the Sea, for it is ſaid <hi>They were all</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception) <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by that reaſon, and upon the account aforeſaid, in reference to the Prophetical Myſterie, Chriſtians Infants may be Baptiſed alſo, even by way of office, otherwiſe we deny grown Chriſtians to have as good a document by <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> as grown <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had by <hi>Infaent Circumciſion,</hi> upon the reſpective accounts betwixt them, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>But this aforeſaid by the way only as a preparative to our further juſtification of <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> by way of <hi>New Diſcovery,</hi> which we
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34694:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>doubt not but <hi>(Chriſto aſſiſtente)</hi> to do, after we have ſet forth more diſtinctly what <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is in its Nomination and Notation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in its Nomination or Notation, comes from the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to waſh or cleanſe, or dip, and anſwers to the Hebr. word. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſaid word is uſed <hi>Ruth</hi> 2.4. and is by <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> rendred <hi>Intinge buccellam in Accto,</hi> dip or waſh thy mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel in the vineager; which ſaid word the Septuagint hath, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Baptiſe or waſh thy morſel in the vineager.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Baptiſm</hi> notes in its nature and ſignification, a waſhing or cleanſing with that which is moſt fit to cleanſe, as Water is moſt experimentally known to be of a mundifying and cleanſing nature, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.4. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is a moſt fit means to figure forth <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> our Spiritual waſhing and cleanſing from all filthineſs of the Fleſh and Spirit, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Hence the Lord Jeſus annexed to his Goſpel Diſpenſation, (which is the Diſpenſation of Faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.) <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> for that the Belief is the purifying Grace and means through the Word (which is indeed the Chriſt of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.11.) to waſh away all remaining defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sin, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence it is ſaid (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26, 27.) Chriſt gave himſelf for his Church, that he might ſanctify and cleanſe it through the Word; and it is ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 15.3. <hi>Now ye are clean through the Word I have ſpoken to you.</hi> And it is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. <hi>He purified their hearts through Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we have in brief offered to conſideration, what <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in general is; and upon what account the Lord Jeſus brought it in, and alſo annext it to his Goſpel Diſpenſation, and how it preſuppoſes Circumciſions work, before it can have its proper operation in its Myſterie upon the ſame real object that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about, which was the Male Infant to be Circumciſed only, and that on the Eighth day only; and that if it were not Circumciſed in that day, then that Male Infant was to be cut off, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence what the Male figured forth, which was the Manly Nature, muſt be alſo conſidered to be Baptiſed or waſhed, and that by Chriſt in his day figured forth in the Eighth day, and if the Manly Nature be not Baptiſed then, by Chriſt in his day, it muſt be cut off from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34694:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Chriſts Spiritual Congregation, which is the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Yet our Saviour ſpecifies and recites none of theſe in his commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for <hi>Baptiſm</hi> by any intimation written, though they muſt be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily underſtood to be Baptiſed alſo, becauſe in the ſame nature wherein the work is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (which is in <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> as aforeſaid) in the ſame it muſt be completed and perfected; and therefore all aforeſaid muſt be underſtood and intended to be Baptiſed alſo upon the account aforeſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the near relating and eſſentially depending of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> (upon the account aforeſaid) betwixt themſelves in reference to the reſpective uſes they are for; reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ſame ſcope and end; yet as aforeſaid, Chriſt mentions not a tittle to that purpoſe in his Ordinance of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it doth inevitably follow, that the Lord Jeſus doth forbear to ſpecifie that again <hi>à parte poſt,</hi> which is ſo clearly expreſt in the <hi>parte ante,</hi> that is expreſſed and appointed in <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence upon the like reaſon we may, and ought to believe, that the Lord Jeſus did intend to allow and warrant <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> by virtue of his Command for <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> upon the reciprocal accounts being a like uſeful, reſpectivelly to the ſame ſcope and end, as a foreſaid.</p>
            <p>The Lord may (we hope none will deny it) make uſe (when he pleaſes) of thoſe rules and maxims he hath taught us to make uſe of upon all occaſions, to prevent multiplicities and tautologies of things, which muſt be underſtood to relate together, as ſpecials under one general, as every <hi>ſpecies</hi> doth under one <hi>genus,</hi> and every member relates reſpectively, in its communication to the integral or whole, to make up its integral, what it is, or ought to be.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>genus,</hi> or the general, is <hi>quod communicat totam ſuam eſſentiam ſuis ſpeciebus,</hi> that is, the general communicates its whole eſſence to its ſpecials under it, as Animal doth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whole eſſence of vegitative and ſenſitive life or virtue to Man and Bruit, alike vegitable and ſenſible; ſo do all members of the integral or whole, communicate their eſſence reſpectively to the whole: hence, ſince generals have their influences in and upon all ſpecials and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars under them reſpectively, they need not be taught and expreſſed in every ſpecial or particular under them reſpectively, but only in one, for that the general is the ſame to every ſpecial in its communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34694:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>reſpectively, as it is to one; and therefore to expreſs it more than once, is but <hi>dem per idem,</hi> and <hi>à fruſtra</hi> (to little purpoſe) <hi>qnod poteſt fieri per pauciora.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that wiſe Artiſts make uſe of the ſaid rule upon due occaſion, We ſhall give you but one inſtance among man,; <hi>Ramus</hi> in his Logick, (the beſt, we believe, <hi>ſecundum regulum,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp; methodum,</hi> that ever (of the many that have) appeared to us) when he hath ſet forth <hi>argumentum</hi> as it is in its uſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and diſtributed it into its conſentany and diſſentany affections reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>vely, he never repeats <hi>argumentum</hi> again, neither in cauſe nor effect, ſubject, nor adjunct, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though it muſt neceſſarily be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood under all the reſpective heads and topicks of Logick, it being the <hi>genus generaliſſimum</hi> to them all reſpectively, yet he doth not repeat it again, <hi>cauſa eſt argumentum cujus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſt, effectum eſt argumentum quod è cauſis exiſtat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> but only ſaith, <hi>cauſa eſt cujus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſt,</hi> leaving out <hi>argumentum,</hi> and ſo out of the reſt; becauſe it being the general, it muſt be underſtood upon the account afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, to have the ſame influence into all the ſpecials under it reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively that it hath to one of them.</p>
            <p>Now ſhall we believe otherwiſe, but that the God of all Arts and Wiſdom (which teacheth others, as aforeſaid, to make uſe of the ſaid maxime) may and doth make uſe of the ſaid rule (in his divine records, commonly called the Scriptures) as he thinks fit to his intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible and rational creatures for brevities ſake, when parallel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of things (as <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baeptiſm</hi> are reſpectively to the ſame end in general, as aforeſaid,) do neceſſarily, and in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency infer the ſame to be alike to the reſpective uſes, though diſſenting in themſelves, as all parts and members are which relate to the whole of which they are members.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> (the two neceſſary Ceremonies for the uſe and uſes aforeſaid,) and ſo neceſſary and eſſentially de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on each other upon the account aforeſaid, <hi>Circumciſion</hi> being the <hi>principium,</hi> the other <hi>finis</hi> of the ſame, and to the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, as aforeſaid; and for that Infants, as Infants, whether <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> or Chriſtians Infants, are all alike in all reſpects to their reſpective <hi>Circumciſion</hi> or <hi>Baptiſm</hi> aforeſaid; We do affirm, that <hi>Infant Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſions</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:34694:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>command, may, and ought to be thought to be allowed its practice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, without a new command upon the account afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that <hi>Generalia generaliter &amp; ſemel docenda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord himſelf declares it, by what is expreſt, <hi>Mark,</hi> 13.37. That he intends that we ſhould take his command, given but to ſome expre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sly, to include all others in like caſe to be conſidered to do, or allowed to do the ſame by virtue of the ſaid command or injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which is appointed thereunto; for when the Lord Jeſus had given an injunction to watch, he explains his intent further, (leaſt others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fter times ſhould think the ſaid injunction concerned not them, but only his preſent Diſciples, to whom he then ſpake) he ſaith <hi>what I ſay to you, I ſay to all,</hi> Watch.</p>
            <p>Hence we ſee it was meant further than to thoſe to whom it was literally ſpoken at preſent, the reaſon is granted, <hi>a pari,</hi> becauſe all are one time or other ſubject and liable to the like dangers and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions reſpectively, that his then preſent Diſciples were, which he warns to take heed of the then dangers.</p>
            <p>And therefore, ſince <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is a parallel in all reſpects, as aforeſaid reſpectively, with <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> to all intents and purpoſes, that they are, and may be applied unto, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>We do with confidence aſſert, that the Lord did intend that we may upon all due occaſions, Baptiſe Infants under the Goſpel, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did Circumciſe their Infants, by his command under the legal diſpenſation; for that one command doth (upon the account aforeſaid) give alike allowance to all perſons and things alike con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, and to be concerned as <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>Infant Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> reſpectively, are to be conſidered in reference to each other, and their end for which they are reſpectively appointed.</p>
            <p>Now it being ſo the rule, <hi>à quatenus ipſum ad de omni effi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ax eſt illatio,</hi> juſtifies <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> upon the account of the ſaid rule; for that the ſaid rule declares, that from one thing or perſon as ſuch, ariſes a prevalent influence to include all to be granted, in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to be owned as ſuch, and ſo under the ſame conſideration to be conſidered reſpectively.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Abraham</hi> is declared to be juſtified only as a Believer, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.22.</p>
            <p>Hence every true Believer may aſſure himſelf upon <hi>Abraham</hi>'s
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34694:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>account aforeſaid, to be juſtified alſo, without being particularly named that he is alſo juſtified; the reaſon is for that an identity and ſameneſs in things, muſt neceſſarily be owned alike to all intents and purpoſes, in whomſoever, or whereſoever it is found reſpectively, which is the aim and ſcope of the rule aforeſaid, <hi>à quatenus ipſum,</hi> &amp;c. in the ſenſe and latitude thereof.</p>
            <p>And it's obſervable which is expreſſed <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 23, 24. that <hi>it was not written for his ſake alone, but for us alſo who believe.</hi> And the reaſon muſt be from, and upon the account of the ſaid rule, that <hi>quatenus ipſum ad de omni,</hi> &amp;c. and may we not ſay therefore, <hi>à pari,</hi> that <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> was not written for <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Infants alone, <hi>in abſtracto,</hi> but for Chriſtians Infants alſo <hi>in concreto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the like account to warrant thereby <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> from <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> though that be only commanded expreſsly, and not <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> in like manner expreſsly; for that <hi>à quatenus ipſum ad de omni efficax eſt illatio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> was commanded only, as <hi>Iſraelites</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were in Infancy, ſuch and ſuch, ſo and ſo. Therefore there is no more reaſon to diſallow of <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> than of <hi>Infant Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> in themſelves reſpectively, to be conſidered in their reſpective Infancies; and as for the command of <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> only, that doth not hinder, but confirm the allowance of <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> upon the account aforeſaid, eſpecially ſince no prohibition (in any caſe) is given againſt <hi>Infant Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> may be practiſed by way of office, and as a good document, be as uſeful to grown Chriſtians upon the acccount aforeſaid, as <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> ever was ordained by way of office likewiſe, and not otherwiſe, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence it's more conſentaneous, and agreeable to reaſon, for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to Baptiſe their Infants, in order to the coming again to the Child-like innocent life (which is the ſole end both of <hi>Circumciſions</hi> and <hi>Baptiſms</hi> Ordination reſpectively, as aforeſaid,) for that <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is the more lively and perſpicuous exemplar of the two, of the attainment unto the Child-like innocent life; becauſe Chriſtians Infants are as innocent as <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Infants could be, and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> being a thorow waſhing (after <hi>Circumciſions</hi> work in its Myſterie is performed,) from all remaining defilements of Fleſh and Spirit.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34694:17"/>
            <p>Hence upon the aforeſaid account, <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is a more ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant and uſeful document and inſtruction, in order to the Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like innocent life and ſtate, than <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> therefore it cannot in reaſon and equity be denyed, but that the Lord did intend its pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice as well as <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> but did not command it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly, becauſe needleſs upon the account of the rules aforeſaid, <hi>generalia generaliter &amp; quatenus ipſum ad de omni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore we cannot in reaſon think, that God gave grown <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſuch a good document and inſtruction, in order to ſignify to them the firſt ſtep unto the Child-like innocent life, by commanding them to Circumciſe their Infants by way of office only, (as aforeſaid) to mind and admoniſh them upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions thereof: but we muſt with like (if not with more) reaſon think, that the Lord doth allow of <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> to mind and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh grown Chriſtians upon all occaſions, duly to endeavour after the completing the Child-like innocent life, as <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in its Myſterie doth ſet forth by a thorow waſhing from all remaining de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements of Sin, after <hi>Circumciſion</hi> in its Myſterie hath cut off the groſs Sins; and therefore the Lord (to his Honour be it ſpoken) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but allow of <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> to be adminiſtred alſo by way of office and as a good document, and reſpectively to grown Chriſtians, by allowing them alſo to Baptiſe their Infants, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were commanded to Circumciſe their Infants upon the like, and no other account, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>We cannot perſuade our ſelves otherwiſe than as aforeſaid, unleſs we do charge the Righteous and Juſt Lord to be more neglective and injurious to grown Chriſtians, than he was to grown <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by not allowing grown Chriſtians alike (if not a more ſignificant) docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and inſtruction (than <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> was) by Baptiſing their Infants, in order to the completing the ſaid Child-like innocent life thereby.</p>
            <p>We hope they will not impoſe upon us to believe, (for fear of unthought of evil conſequences to follow thereupon) that God did command <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> and did intend to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>own <hi>Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> only upon his own meer authoritative will and pleaſure without any further reaſon but his meer Will for the ſaid commanding <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> and diſowning <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> which is as uſeful and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34694:17"/>ſignificant to all intents and purpoſes, as ever <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was, for no other reaſon, but becauſe he would: this we cannot yield unto, for that Gods Infinite Wiſdom is previous and foregoing to all his Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks, as it is expreſſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.24. <hi>O Lord how manifold are thy Works! in wiſdom thou haſt made them all.</hi> Hence in great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (and no otherwiſe) did the Lord ordain <hi>Infant Circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore he could not out of meer will and pleaſure diſown <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi> for that if he do, he doth diſown that which is as rational and uſeful upon the account of all like reſpects betwixt <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> as ever <hi>Circumciſion</hi> was.</p>
            <p>This they dare not ſtand unto, and therefore ask them why the Lord ſhould own <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> and command it, and yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> which Chriſtians Infants are as capable of to all intents and purpoſes, as <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Infants were of <hi>Infant Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ask them the reaſon aforeſaid, they anſwer (for a ſhift, as we have heard from ſome, not knowing a better reaſon for it, for want of ſearching into Divine Writ for a better:)</p>
            <p>That God (ſay they) did it to diſtinguiſh <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Infants from Heathens Children; whereas indeed that reaſon for it, is more frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, than <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is; for that Heathens ſeldom ſee (unleſs by accident) <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Infants in that age, to ſhew their <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> and we judge that the grown <hi>Iſraelites Circumciſion</hi> was more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious for that purpoſe, for that they could give the grown Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens a particular account of their <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> Wherefore their God commanded them to be Circumciſed, but yet take their afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid reaſon for <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> as it is, and then retort it upon them, and tell them that they confeſs thereby that God commanded <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> by way of office only, for that is no more (by their Confeſſion) than a repreſentative to Heathens for the end aſſigned, as aforeſaid; and it's all we aver, and ſay, (but in a better ſenſe) that God did command <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> by way of office only, and to be a fit document and inſtruction to grown <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> as hath been demonſtrated upon the accounts and ends ſet forth, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> being ſo commanded, we ſay it's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded upon no other grounds, than upon what <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> may
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34694:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>be practiſed, that is, by way of office and good document unto grown Chriſtians, as hath been often (for memories cauſe) expreſſed, and urged.</p>
            <p>Now it being ſo, that <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is not urged for its practice, but only by way of office, which is the ſame that contradicents to <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> confeſs, as it's proved from their own confeſſion is commanded for.</p>
            <p>Hence we ſay that there was no need for a new command for to warrant <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> upon the account aforeſaid, for its Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration; for that there is one before, <hi>viz.</hi> for <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> adminiſtred by way of office only, and it being ſo; the antient pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed rules atteſt and warrant another thing to be done by way of like office alſo, as <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is with <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, which ſaid ancient maxims are theſe enſuing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Generalia generalitèr, &amp; ſemel docenda: à quatenus ipſum ad de omni efficax eſt illatio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Generals are to be taught generally, and at once.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That from ſuch and ſuch, ſo and ſo, ariſeth a prevalent Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and concluding of another like thing, as ſuch and ſuch, ſo and ſo, in like manner both theſe rules are founded in the head of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates in Logick, <hi>à paribus</hi> from likeneſſes betwixt things that are to be conſidered as adequate and alike reſpectively, in reference to each other, as <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is with <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> by way of office, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>We can give many inſtances for the practice of the firſt named maxim <hi>generaliter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ramus</hi> (mentioned before) never names <hi>argumentum</hi> but once, (after its diſtribution) though it have its influence in and upon every head of Logick, becauſe its <hi>genus generaliſſimum,</hi> the chief general to them all as ſpecials under it, for <hi>genus communicat totam ſuam eſsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſuis ſpeciebus,</hi> that is, the general communicates its whole ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral eſſence to all ſpecials under it.</p>
            <p>Inſtance: <hi>Animal</hi> doth in like manner communicate the vegitative and ſenſitive virtue and life to Man and Beaſt.</p>
            <p>And therefore to expreſs a general more than once, is needleſs; for that it's <hi>idem per idem,</hi> the ſame by the ſame; and the rule is, <hi>fruſtra fit per plura quod poteſt fieri per pauciora;</hi> it's a <hi>frnſtra,</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34694:18"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to little purpoſe to do a thing by many things, which may be done by fewer.</p>
            <p>Hence the ſaid rule for and by teaching generals at once is pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, to prevent needleſs tautologies, and repetitions of things alike to be conſidered, and may be underſtood by one, and at once.</p>
            <p>And is it not a needleſs repetition to recite a new Command for warranting <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> when the Lord hath given one before for <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> which was adminiſtred upon no other nor better account, than <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> may be adminiſtred alſo?</p>
            <p>And ſince it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o betwixt <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> reſpectively, that rule alſo, <hi>à quatenus ipſum ad de omni,</hi> juſtifies <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> though it have no expreſs command for its practice, yet it's as truly warranted as <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> is, though it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; yea, and by virtue of the ſaid command, for that <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> is ſuch and ſuch, ſo and ſo, as <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> is ſuch and ſuch, ſo and ſo, in reference to the ſame uſe and end reſpectively, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>It's ſaid that <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified only as a Believer, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Hence every true Believer may aſſure himſelf (upon the account of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Juſtification) that he is Juſtified alſo, though he be not named by an expreſs to be Juſtified alſo.</p>
            <p>And it's aſſured him from the rule <hi>à quatenus ipſum,</hi> as aforeſaid; for that he is ſuch and ſuch, ſo and ſo; and therefore needs no new naming of him juſtified, but his true Belief by Faith is ſufficient, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s was.</p>
            <p>For that an identity and ſameneſs muſt neceſſarily be owned in one as well as the other, where it is found.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the contradicents to <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> do ſo tenaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adhere to the having a particular Command for their practice of a duty to be done upon Scripture account and liking, as they do for the practice of <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi> or they will not (as they do not) own the practice of it.</p>
            <p>We ſhall offer to their ſerious conſideration that expreſs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.4. concerning Oxen, <hi>Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the Oxe when he treadeth out the Corn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle makes uſe of the ſaid naked command, concerning muzzling the mouth of the Oxe in the caſe aforeſaid; ſaying, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34694:19"/>
               <hi>Doth God take care for Oxen?</hi> (as to fill his Divine Records with Commands for them, which are intentionally writtten for more Heavenly concerns than Oxen,) <hi>or ſaith he that altogether for our ſakes? for our ſakes no doubt this is written,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) who would have thought the ſaid Command concerning the Oxe, had been intended (unleſs the Apoſtle had declared ſo much) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be a Command in ſpecial, concerning the livelyhood of Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Miniſters, of which there is not a tittle in the ſaid Scripture, neither before nor after; yet the Apoſtle doth apply it to be chiefly intended for the providing and giving livelyhood to Evangelical Miniſters; ſo alſo, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18.</p>
            <p>Now wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrant for ſo doing? ſurely no other, but only from <hi>argumentum de comparatis,</hi> viz. <hi>à minori ad magis;</hi> that is, from comparates of the leſs to the greater, which is, that if the Lord commanded ſo concerning the Oxe, He meant it to be underſtood more eſpecially concerning Evangelical Miniſters livelyhood, though he did not expreſs ſo much therein.</p>
            <p>And may We not ſay the like for and concerning <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> from Gods command for <hi>Infant Circumciſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That God intended thereby his allowance, or warrant for <hi>Infant Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For can we think that God had ſuch care for <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> as to command that, and altogether paſs by his taking notice of <hi>Infant Baptiſm:</hi> whereas it's as rational, uſeful, and documental in being adminiſtred by way of office, as ever <hi>Circumciſion was,</hi> which was adminiſtred only by way of office, as aforeſaid; and <hi>Infant Baptiſms</hi> Adminiſtration by way of office, doth repreſent and hold forth a more lively and perſpicuons document, in reference to the end both of <hi>Circumciſions</hi> and <hi>Baptiſms</hi> work, for which they were brought in reſpectively, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>à minori ad magis</hi> alſo; that is, from the leſs to the greater, betwixt <hi>Infant Circumciſion &amp; Infant Baptiſm;</hi> for that <hi>Infant Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> being the leſs ſignificant by way of office, than <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> upon their reſpective conſiderations is, in reference to the attaining unto the Child-like innocent life and ſtate.</p>
            <p>It cannot in reaſon be denyed, but that God did intend by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> to warrant the practice of <hi>Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:34694:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo without a command; or truly, as the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Cor.</hi> that God intended there ſhould be the allowance of Evangelical Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters livelihood; by his only commanding <hi>not to muzzle the mouth of the Oxe,</hi> though he did not give command for it alſo, as he did for the Oxe.</p>
            <p>All aforeſaid for the adjuſting <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſiderations aforeſaid, in reference to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, muſt (as we perſuade ourſelves they will) be yielded unto, or we ſhall at laſt intangle our ſelves, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were intangled, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. in ſuch enſuing evil conſequences by our not yielding, as will infer many unworthy (we are afraid blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous) reflections upon the Lord Jeſus, by his neither commanding, nor forbidding <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi> for that all the long &amp; violent conteſts among conſcientious Chriſtians have been thereupon, becauſe the Lord hath not forbidden, nor commanded it.</p>
            <p>Hence, one party diſowns it, becauſe it is not commanded: the other party pleading for it, and practiſing it, (as they may) becauſe it is not forbidden.</p>
            <p>Now, if the Lord had pleaſed to have commanded, or forbidden <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi> ſurely the ſad and known conteſts about it, had (we are more than confident) never been.</p>
            <p>Hence we do <hi>ex fine rei,</hi> and upon the matter, make the Lord to be <hi>(abſit bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſphemia dicto)</hi> the firſt author of them all, for it's a true maxim, <hi>Quod eſt cauſae cauſae, eſt cauſa cauſati: in cauſis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatè dependentibus inter ſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, the cauſe of a cauſe immediatly depending on each other, is the firſt cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the thing cauſed thereby.</p>
            <p>Now ſince all the conteſts that have been about <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> for that the Lord hath neither commanded it, nor forbidden it, as he might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly have done either.</p>
            <p>Hence we make him <hi>cauſam,</hi> at leaſt <hi>cauſam ſine quânon,</hi> of all conteſts about <hi>Infant Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a ſtory (whether true or feigned it matters not, for <hi>ficta arguunt fidemque faciunt,</hi> as that of the Trees) <hi>Judges</hi> 9.8. (that went forth to chooſe a King) of a very ſtrife lover Parent, who when he looked to die, made his laſt Will and Teſtament ſo dark and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous for ſenſe and meaning, on purpoſe his Children ſhould not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34694:20"/>know in expreſs words his reſpective intentions towards them in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to his laſt Will and Teſtament; ſaying to himſelf, it doth me good to think how my Children will contend and quarrel among themſelves after my death concerning my words towards them in my laſt Will and Teſtament.</p>
            <p>We forbear the application relatively to Chriſt's laſt Will and Teſtament.</p>
            <p>But yet if the Lord Jeſus did not intend that his command for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Circumciſion</hi> ſhould adjuſt the warrant for <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> without more ado; We infer, the Lord Jeſus to deal <hi>ex fine rei</hi> upon the matter, as darkly and ambiguouſly in his laſt Will and T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtament (in reference to <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi>) as the ſtrife lover Parent did in his laſt Will and Teſtament, as aforeſaid: As if the Lord Jeſus were pleaſed (by his neither commanding nor forbidding <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi>) with all the ſaid conteſts and ſtrifes that have riſen among his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Diſciples about it.</p>
            <p>This muſt follow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon the Lords own teſtimony in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe, <hi>à pari, Prov.</hi> 8.36. where it's ſaid by the Spirit of God, <hi>all that hate me love death,</hi> that is, the damnable death.</p>
            <p>But who loves that? for <hi>nemo vult ſui deſtructionem,</hi> ſaid a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
            <p>Yet becauſe he that hates God, which conſiſts in a ſeparated life from God, doth bring the ſaid inevitable death upon himſelf, as if he loved it.</p>
            <p>And ſo we frequently uſe the expreſſion of loving that miſery and puniſhment we bring upon our ſelves (knowingly and voluntarily) which is annexed by aſſignment unto the ſame.</p>
            <p>As when we ſay to a Thief taken in the fact, that he longed to be hanged, when he deſires nothing leſs in his affections.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>à pari,</hi> it muſt <hi>(ex vi conſequentiae)</hi> follow, if the Lord doth not command, nor forbid <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> by reaſon whereof all the conteſts and ſtrifes about it have riſen, that he is charged (if the command for <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> was not intended to warrant its practice) to be at leaſt the <hi>cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> that is the cauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the conteſts about <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> had not been among con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious and profeſſing Chriſtians.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:34694:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Hence we do ſtick to it, and affirm with more than confidence, that God intended his command for <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> (upon the parallel reſpects betwixt <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> as aforeſaid) ſhould declare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> allowance of the practice of <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> about which there hath been ſuch bitter oppoſition, by reaſon the Lord hath neither commanded it, nor forbidden it.</p>
            <p>God hates, eſpecially among his conſcientious Diſciples, all ſuch conteſts and quarrels; For firſt, he is (as he is truly ſtiled in a known place) <hi>the Author of Peace, and Lover of Concord,</hi> and calls all his Diſciples to peace.</p>
            <p>And is the true <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who warns his Brethren not to fall out by the way, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.24. but <hi>endeavour to keep the unity of the Spirit, and the bond of Peace, Epheſ.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <p>Hence, ſurely the Lord Jeſus would not have been ſo negligent, careleſs, unmindful (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) as neither to command, or forbid <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> to have prevented the ſtrifes aforeſaid (between two well meaning parties) about it; for that they are ſo contrary, (eſpecially to break forth among his profeſſing Diſciples,) to his own inclination to Peace and Concord, ſo much, and in divers places declared in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Upon all which aforeſaid, let us penſitate and weigh that good and wholſom expreſs in <hi>Publick Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doubt ye not, but be well perſwaded for the time to come, oh ye contradicents of <hi>Infant Baptiſm!</hi> that God allows and owns that charitable work of ours in bringing Infants to his Holy <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> for that they are (being Baptiſed) as good a document of remembrance to grown Chriſtians upon the account aforeſaid, as ever <hi>Infant Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> was, though commanded; but yet commanded upon no other account, but by way of office, as aforeſaid reſpectively, by which Chriſtians Infants ought, and no otherwiſe to be Baptiſed.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not preſume to trouble the contradicents to <hi>Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> further, by multiplying more ſeeming arguments <hi>in specie</hi> for it, which yet <hi>in re verâ</hi> will be but repetitions, and <hi>idem per idem,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the maxime, <hi>generalia generalitèr, &amp; ſemel dicenda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore we deſire them ſeriouſly to examine what we have here offered to conſideration, in reference to the Juſtification of <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> by our (through Gods direction) <hi>New Diſcovery</hi> of the way and means thereof, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:34694:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Yet give us leave to ſay, for a further illuſtration of the more than probable intention of the Lord to wrap up his allowance and owning <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> in his command for <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally not prohibiting it, without a repetition of another command for <hi>Infant Baptiſm;</hi> for that the Spirit of Wiſdom doth frequently in Holy Writ fold up for many cauſes very much in little, or in half that which is intended, and muſt be explicated reſpectively to make the ſenſe and ſcope of the portion of Scripture (where it is) full and compleat, to the purpoſe that the ſaid Scripture is appointed for.</p>
            <p>And there are many inſtances thereof in Holy Writ; but we will offer but two at preſent. One is in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.6. where it's ſaid, <hi>the Lord knows the way of the righteous, but the way of the wicked ſhall periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt part of the ſaid Verſe, there muſt be ſuppoſed to make the ſenſe thereof full and perſpicuous, the contrary to that which is expreſt in the latter part of the Ver. <hi>(viz.) the way of the wicked ſhall periſh,</hi> which is, <hi>the way of the righteous ſhall be preſerved,</hi> for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is contrary to periſhing.</p>
            <p>Hence two axioms in the ſaid part of the Verſe, one apparent, <hi>the Lord owns the way of the righteous;</hi> the other latent, which is this, the Lord ſaith, <hi>therefore the Lord preſerves the way of the righteous;</hi> the reaſon is, becauſe the righteous and wicked are contraries; and therefore, if <hi>the way of the wicked ſhall periſh,</hi> therefore <hi>the way of the righteous ſhall be preſerved;</hi> and it's for that the Lord owns the <hi>way of the righteous,</hi> therefore his way <hi>ſhall be preſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the latter part of the Verſe is poſitively atteſted, that <hi>the way of the wicked ſhall periſh,</hi> the reaſon is clear, when the contrary to the firſt part of the Verſe is added and expreſſed, which is, the Lord diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owns the <hi>way of the wicked,</hi> as he owns the <hi>way of the righteous</hi> upon the account that whether we are wicked or righteous; therefore he diſowns the <hi>way of the wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Proverbs of <hi>Solomon</hi> are full of ſuch <hi>latent</hi> and <hi>tacit</hi> diſpoſures of Scriptures; but we ſhall give you but one inſtance of the very many ſo couched there, as aforeſaid; which ſaid inſtance is in <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Only by pride,</hi> (or <hi>raſhneſs</hi> rather) <hi>cometh contention, but with the well adviſed is wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:34694:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>There muſt be theſe axioms laid down in the firſt part of the Verſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Folly is the attendant of Pride or Raſhneſs.</item>
               <item>2. Therefore by Pride, (or Raſhneſs rather,) cometh contention. In the latter part of the Verſe theſe two axioms.
<list>
                     <item>1. Wiſdom attends the well adviſed.</item>
                     <item>2. Therefore with the well adviſed there is peace and quietneſs.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt part of the Verſe is ſupplyed Folly, the contrary to Wiſdom, ſpecified in the latter part of the Verſe.</p>
            <p>And in the latter part is ſupplyed the contrary to Contention in the firſt part of the Verſe.</p>
            <p>Which contrary is Peace and Quietneſs; and ſo the full ſenſe and ſcope of the ſaid Verſe is laid down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the demonſtration of the cauſe of Raſhneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> Folly with Raſhneſs is the cauſe of all contention.</p>
            <p>In the latter part of the Verſe is laid down the cauſe of well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedneſs, which is Wiſdom; and that being with the well adviſed, it cauſeth and preſerveth Peace and Quietneſs, which is the contrary to Contention in the firſt part of the Verſe.</p>
            <p>Thus it appears how the Spirit of God doth in Holy Writ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and wrap up many depending axioms, which are requiſitely to be ſupplyed to explicate the intended ſenſe and ſcope in them for brevities ſake.</p>
            <p>And the ground and warrant of the contraction by <hi>latent</hi> and <hi>tacit</hi> diſpoſures of them in the portions of Scriptures where they are, is from the rule of contraries in Logick; for that contraries are ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites, that <hi>uno affirmato, alterum negatur,</hi> and <hi>uno negato, alterum affirmatur,</hi> becauſe they do <hi>ratione &amp; re inter ſe diſſentire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, contraries are ſuch oppoſites, that one being affirmed, the other muſt be denyed, and one being denyed, the other muſt be affirmed; becauſe ſuch oppoſites both in Logical reſpect, or reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive reaſonings; and in alſo their reſpective natures &amp; beings, oppoſe one another, as the righteous and wicked do.</p>
            <p>And therefore where ſuch oppoſites are diſpoſed together, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent can draw forth for the reſpective uſes, ſuch <hi>latent</hi> and <hi>tacit</hi> axioms out of thoſe that are mentioned and expreſſed in the ſaid Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; As the Lord knows or owns the way of the righteous, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he diſowns the way of the wicked, becauſe the wicked is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in his way to the way of the righteous.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:34694:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>So the <hi>way of the wicked ſhall periſh,</hi> as it is expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>way of the righteous ſhall be ſafe,</hi> or preſerved; for that the wicked and righteous ones ways (owned and diſowned) are contraries, as in the firſt part of the Verſe declared.</p>
            <p>So in <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.10. <hi>By Pride or raſhneſs cometh contention,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with well adviſedneſs, or with the well adviſed is quietneſs and peace; for that raſhneſs and well adviſedneſs are oppoſite contraries; and therefore, if by raſhneſs cometh contention, it muſt follow <hi>a contrariis contrariariorum conſequentiis</hi> that is, from the contrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentials of conſequences; from well adviſedneſs comes peace and quietneſs.</p>
            <p>So if Wiſdom is the attendant of well adviſedneſs as it's expreſt to be in the Verſe, <hi>with the well adviſed is wiſdom;</hi> for that is the cauſe of well adviſedneſs, and the guide of the well adviſed.</p>
            <p>Therefore by the rule of contraries, as aforeſaid, Folly is the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant and cauſe of raſhneſs, for that is the oppoſite to Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Now if all ſuch portions of Scripture (wherein ſuch <hi>latent</hi> and <hi>tacit</hi> diſpoſures of axioms are contained, as are in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 1.6. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.10. (in which Book multitudes are contained) were expreſly, <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; uno intuitu,</hi> laid forth, that is, opened at once, and together; how voluminous and big would they ſwell the Bible unto? even too big for a Pocket reception, and a <hi>Vade Mecum</hi> upon the account aforeſaid. Neither could the Bible be read over ſo ſoon and often, with all the axioms relating to the ſaid reſpective portions of Scriptures, and explained (as they muſt be) to make the intent and ſcope of them appear to open view, as they do being diſpoſed as they now are, by the ſupplies added out of each contrary, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Lord in great Wiſdom, diſpoſed multitudes of Divine axioms in Holy Writ for brevities cauſe, and ends and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And may we not (in like manner) think that the Lord omitted his Command for <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> though he allow and own it upon the reſpective accounts aforeſaid betwixt it and <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> in reference to their reſpective Adminiſtrations for brevities cauſe, and to avoid needleſs repetitions; which if he had commanded it expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet it had not been (nor could be) upon any other account than that which he gave for <hi>Infant Circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:34694:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>for which it was to be done by way of office only, and good docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to others concerns at preſent, not their own; and therefore ſince <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> may be done by way of office alſo, and to as good purpoſe as ever <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> was, it was needleſs (with reverence be it ſpoken) for the Lord to repeat a new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> alſo, for that upon the account aforeſaid, it had been (we believe) but a tautology <hi>idem ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> idem</hi> that is the ſame to which went before <hi>ex fine rei</hi> upon the matter, if he had given another Command for <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>Thus we have offered to conſideration the ſeveral grounds and reaſons why the Lord might omit (upon rational grounds,) to give a Command for <hi>Infant Baptiſm,</hi> and could give no prohibition againſt <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> upon the account before demonſtrated betwixt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>Infant Circumciſion,</hi> we have now we hope ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently argued the demonſtration of Juſtification of <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> by a <hi>New Diſcovery;</hi> which Diſcovery is found out by the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe two great and uſeful Sacraments or Myſteries, <hi>(viz.) Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which the Lord appointed and brought in, and annexed to his reſpective diſpenſations Legal and Evangelical, for ſuch uſes and ends as are before declared, and that for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of two great impediments, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the groſs Sins, firſt by <hi>Circumciſion</hi> in its Myſterie; and then the remaining defilements (that for ſome time continue until w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhed away, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in its Myſterie, both which the groſs Sins and remaining defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sin, do impede and obſtruct (until removed) the coming back again to the Child-like innocent life and ſtate which our Saviour declares to be done for an entrance into the Kingdom of Heaven; Therefore he ſets a little Child in the midſt of his Diſciples, <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.3. and then declares ſo much unto them, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> upon the account aforeſaid, were brought in by way of office only, as repreſentitavely documental, and teaching in their reſpective Myſteries in reference to the ends and purpoſes they were appointed for, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And for that our Saviour declares the Child-like innocent life to be the pattern and exemplar to which <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in their reſpective operations do relate and tend unto reſpectively,</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:34694:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Hence the Lord ordained <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> to repreſent the ſaid Child l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke innocent life and ſtate by way of office and good docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as aforeſaid, to grown <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at preſent, to mind them thereof what rule of life they muſt look unto, and alſo by both <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> to relating and depending operations reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, as aforeſaid; and therefore both are to be received only by way of office, and that in reference to others, not themſelves at preſent.</p>
            <p>And We believe alſo, that moſt of the Bible, eſpecially the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical parts of it, of things done, or not to be done; or otherwiſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, are not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itten for ſuch uſe and end as the letter of them ſeems to expreſs; but for higher concerns by way of office deſigned by God thereunto, though they be declared in literal expreſſes, yet not to be done upon literal accounts only, as they ſeem to hold forth.</p>
            <p>For can We imagine that the Holy and Infinite Wiſe God, who knows things <hi>(intus &amp; in cutè,)</hi> paſt, preſent, and to come, would cauſe a Volum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be compiled of ſo low and ſordid things, as the letter doth expreſs and for no other Myſteries under them, and to cauſe it to be called his Holy Bible, and Sacred Word of his, moſt profitable for inſtruction of good manners according to Divine Truth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of evil manners, comfort of dejected ones for want of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Heavenly preſence; to make them of a Holy and Heavenly life, and to exhort them that are too ſlow in purſuing of good, and and to dehort th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whoſe feet are too ſwift to run after evil, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17.</p>
            <p>Thus we cannot imagine, that the Lord would ſuffer his ſaid Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> filled with ſo many expreſſes, as in letter they ſeem to look to be done the clear contrary way.</p>
            <p>Therefore We believe, they all hold forth ſomthing or other by way of office and good document, to repreſent the way and means by which the fallen Humanity is to be made (through their Myſterie) better towards its amendment to piety again, or whereby the wicked and persevering evil Humanity grows worſe and worſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            <p>And ſo was that of <hi>Lot</hi>'s daughters practiſes, in reference to entice and perſuade their Father, and his yielding and complying with ſuch a wickedneſs, as the letter of the Scripture ſeems to hold out; for that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34694:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>it is ſo contrary to Nature, and againſt the Law of Naitons, like that as is mentioned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2.</p>
            <p>Yet neither they, nor <hi>Lot</hi> their Father have any reflection of evil for what they did reſpectively, but all paſſed over in ſilence, without mentioning any failing in them, but declaring their reſpective fact, without mentioning more than what they did.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſome better Myſtery was intended and deſigned under what was done, than what the letter ſeems to hold forth; nor was that true in the letter Ver. 31, That there was not a Man in the Earth (if we take the Earth for the habitable World) to come in unto them after the manner of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Earth; for there were then many they might have married with, and ſome of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed alſo.</p>
            <p>Hence ſome further deſign muſt be intended then that under the letter, and that of a good document, for that <hi>God</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>James,</hi> Chap 1.) <hi>tempts no man to evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacob Beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> (no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch contemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ible Writer as many account him) tells us in his <hi>Myſterium magnum</hi> on the ſaid Scripture, of a more ſublime and documentally uſeful deſign the Lord had in ordering all the ſaid tranſactions betwixt <hi>Lot</hi>'s daughters, and of <hi>Lot</hi> their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be as they are Recorded.</p>
            <p>And who can perſuade themſelves, that <hi>Lot,</hi> who is called a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, and vexed his righteous Soul, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. with the unclean converſation of the <hi>Sodomites?</hi> ſhould do ſuch an horrid evil as the letter doth expreſs? for then the Poets Verſe he had verified in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<q>Turpe eſt doctori cum culpa redarguit ipſa.</q> For he that was vexed with the unclean converſation of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> committed a more foul uncleanneſs himſelf, if the letter be there true of what they did without a Myſterie; Therefore we ought to decline ſuch like conceptions of ſuch Holy Men as <hi>Lot</hi> is recorded to be.</p>
            <p>And ſurely Holy Men of God (who ſpake that, and all Scripture, as they were moved by the Holy-Ghoſt) would not have recorded thoſe facts of Saints; and if they had; then with ſome monition annexed to the publication of them, but nothing of blemiſh to them is hinted in the ſaid Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:34694:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>If the words that be here publiſhed by Holy Men, be to ſet forth <hi>Lot</hi>'s Daughters, and <hi>Lot</hi>'s practiſes as their unnatural wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Then thoſe Holy men who writ them, did moſt contrary to <hi>David</hi>'s advice, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. <hi>Tell it not in</hi> Gath, <hi>nor publiſh it in</hi> Askelon.</p>
            <p>Not in <hi>Gath,</hi> wraths Wine preſs, where profane perſons ſqueeze out the dregs of higheſt reproach (upon all occaſions) of facts recorded in Scripture, done by moſt eminent Saints of God.</p>
            <p>The Natrative of <hi>Jacobs</hi> having ſo many Wives together; and the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> ſo many Concub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes: How do carnal and vitious men abuſe it to a liberty of the Fleſh, even to the committing great folly in <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They thereupon take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> liberty to have many Wives together, if not in one place, yet in many and in divers Countreys; at leaſt many Concubines, becauſe the Antients had ſo, when as in the beginning God appointed to the Man but one Wife; and the reaſon is given, <hi>Mal</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.15. <hi>Becauſe he ſought a godly Seed;</hi> and Our Saviour told the <hi>Phariſees</hi> upon their cavilous quaerie to Him, <hi>Matt.</hi> 15.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. that from the beginning it was not ſo; Therefore it's alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether contrary to the firſt Inſtitution of Marriage in the Innocent ſtate, and after the fallen humanity returns to his God again, it will be in the ſaid caſe as in the beginning, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>But becauſe they find in Holy Writ, that the old Fathers had many Wives, and that the Wives laid their Handmaids by their Husbands, therefore they pervert the Divine deſign of God to a carnal (and ſomtimes profane) abuſe, and meaning quite contrary to Gods ſaid deſign in his permiſſion aforeſaid, <hi>whoſe ways are not the carnal Mans ways: nor His thoughts their thoughts,</hi> Iſai. 55.8. As it was told by a very ſober perſon in the preſence of divers, that <hi>Sarah</hi> (whom St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpecifies, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6.) to be an Exemplar of Piety in her Converſation, was the firſt Bawd who gave her Maid-Servant to her Husband <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <q>Quis talia fando temperat?—</q>
            </p>
            <p>For that it was told in <hi>Gath,</hi> (as the letter expreſſes it) wraths Wine-preſs to ſqueez out reproach againſt the Saints of God, <hi>whoſe ways are not their ways,</hi> but above their ſight, as they ſtand recorded in Scripture; and what was told in <hi>Askelon,</hi> where falſe weights are uſed; (as <hi>Askelon</hi> ſignifies) which thoſe the malitious and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34694:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>envious <hi>Jews</hi> uſed betwixt Chriſt and <hi>Barrabas,</hi> in that they rejected Chriſt, and choſe <hi>Barrabas</hi> a notorious robber; it falls out ſo often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that a leſs offence is aggravated againſt Saints that fail, as <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. are ſpread abroad with great inſulting, when notorious practiſes of vitious men are hid, if poſſible; but if they cannot, then leſſened and excuſed with and by the recorded ſayings of the Saints, as <hi>Noah, Lot,</hi> and <hi>David, &amp;c.</hi> who ſtand recorded upon higher accounts by the Spirit of Gods direction, than they are capable to underſtand in the blindneſs of their underſtandings; Thus the fleſhly reaſon doth abuſe the reſpective Narratives of the Saints actions of ſuch and ſuch, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>For the ſaid Fathers had their communion with God, and his Heavenly Spirit, and performed their Services in the Houre of God, the heart of Humanity, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3. in and through the Spirit of God, neither could they perform any Services acceptable to God, without the Heavenly Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>But the earthly Spirits of natural reaſon take no regard (as a <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> ſaith) to the Spirit of the Lord, if ſo be they have but the letter, they are content to reſt in its naked expreſs, and thereupon take the things recorded only as the letter expreſſes them.</p>
            <p>Whereupon it comes to paſs, that the carnal figurative man thinks the Divine and Spiritual Ordinances, are for the moſt part made uſe of for an earthly luſt in the Fleſh; and then declare and ſay, the Lord ſo meant and intended it, for that the Holy Scriptures hold it out in the expreſs letter of them.</p>
            <p>And ſo it doth, that men are trees, and <hi>Herod</hi> a Fox, yet they are to ſignify ſome further conſiderations as they will confeſs, which yet in many other things they will not yield that higher Myſteries are under them, but ſtick to the letter, and miſtake thereby moſt of the Ordinances and Services which they take out of the letter, and ſay, the Scripture is written (as it is acknowledged) by the Holy Spirit, which muſt be our rule; and he that will deny it, that the Holy Spirit hath not ſo meant it as they fancie, through the blindneſs of their earthly reaſon, then he muſt be a Seducer and an Heretick that ſaith otherwiſe than they ſay; whereas under the ſaid letter other things (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Jews, Gal.</hi> 4.4.) are meant; and <hi>Jacob Behem</hi> declares, that Divine and Heavenly Myſteries are meant by and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34694:25"/>through the practiſes of <hi>Lot</hi>'s Daughters, and of <hi>Lot</hi> himſelf, as he ſaith, for that the antient Fathers recorded in the Old Teſtament, had their communion with God, and his Heavenly Spirit, neither could they perform their Services in the Houſe of God, the heart of the Humanity, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.6. acceptable to God without the Heavenly Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>But the earthly Spirits of natural reaſon take no heed that there is further meaning and intention of the Spirit of God under the letter; but if they have the plain letter expreſs, then they are content in and with their Services (without minding whether the Spirit of God have a further and more ſecret meaning under the letter, yea owned) as it had under the two Mountains, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24, 25.</p>
            <p>And they ſay the Scriptures are written by the Holy-Ghoſt; and it's confeſt ſo they are: but yet the Spirit of the Lord muſt open that within the vale, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15.) before they can know the mind of God in the ſaid Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.10, 11. which are, and muſt be our rule of direction.</p>
            <p>Yet they are ſo confident they know the Scriptures ſenſe, by what the letter holds out, as they will not depart from it, though they may read in the ſame Scriptures how the learned <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> miſtook the letter of the Scriptures, to the cauſing of great conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious among themſelves concerning Chriſt, that he could not be a Prophet, ſee <hi>John</hi> 7, <hi>ver.</hi> 40. to <hi>ver.</hi> 53. what bandying there was among them about our Lord; ſome whoſe hearts were opened, (as <hi>Lydia's</hi> was) did affirm him to be the Prophet; ſome that he was the Chriſt: But the Scripture learned denyed it upon the account of the place from whence he came, <hi>(viz.) Galilee;</hi> therefore he could not be the Chriſt, for that the Scripture ſaith ſo, affirm the learned that Chriſt came of the Seed of <hi>David,</hi> and out of the Town of <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> and how incenſed were they againſt <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> for wiſhing them to conſider their Law that condemns no man before it hear him, and know what he doth.</p>
            <p>They asked him if he were of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and bid him ſearch and look, they meant in the Scripture letter ſurely; For out of <hi>Galilee</hi> ariſeth no Prophet. But if theſe learned men had not been blinded in their carnal reaſon, but underſtood that the Lord appointed all theſe names by way of office as ſignificants of further Myſteries under the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34694:25"/>ſaid literal names, then they would not have been ſo confident in their <hi>we ſay, and no ſay,</hi> for in their Myſterie; all theſe aforeſaid ſpecifications, (ſome whereof they owned, but ignorantly) the other they denyed, that a Prophet doth not ariſe out of <hi>Galilee,</hi> which yet there doth ariſe Prophets; and Chriſt the Prophet alſo there, as <hi>Galilee</hi> in its word ſignifies Converſion or turning about, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Gods deſign to the new life by repentance; therefore ſo much is ſpoken of Chriſts appearing to his Diſciples in <hi>Galilee,</hi> that is, in their turning about to him; and ſo much is expreſſed of Chriſts going into <hi>Galilee,</hi> and Preaching in <hi>Galilee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So it was alſo true that Chriſt was of the Seed of <hi>David</hi> in the Myſterie, as <hi>David</hi> in his office figures forth, which is the lovely Service.</p>
            <p>So Chriſt came out of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> the houſe of Bread, as that Town in its name figureth forth; and doth not Chriſt ſay of himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 6.49, 50. that He is <hi>the Bread that came down from Heaven?</hi> ſo of the City of <hi>Nazareth</hi> was <hi>Nathaniel</hi> alſo miſtaken in, and that out of the letter.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid to him, <hi>John</hi> 1.45. of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Law, and the Prophets did write.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth <hi>the Son of</hi> Joſeph: <hi>Nathaniel</hi> replies, <hi>Can any good thing come out of</hi> Nazareth? this he gathered from the letter only, for that it was a contemptible City; and yet <hi>Matt.</hi> 21.11. the multitude confeſs that he was Jeſus the Prophet of <hi>Nazareth</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and to that City was the Angel ſent to <hi>Mary, Luke</hi> 1.26. It was a City of <hi>Galilee;</hi> Now all theſe had under their reſpective literal names, their reſpective Myſteries contained. And can we think otherwiſe, when the Spirit of God cauſeth the ſaid reſpective names to be ſo punctually recorded, it cannot be without ſuch a deſign; for as the Apoſtle ſaith 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. Doth God take ſuch care for Oxen, as to cauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> to write a Law for them, without a further or higher concern than Oxen.</p>
            <p>And ſo doth the Spirit of God cauſe ſo many Scripture names for Ciphers, only to be written without a deſign of greater Myſteries under them, which the learned Scribes were ignorant of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore denyed Chriſt to be a Prophet, and the Chriſt of God, for that he cometh out of <hi>Galilee;</hi> and out of <hi>Nazareth</hi> they thought no good thing could come.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:34694:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And <hi>Nathaniel</hi> thought ſo for a time, that no good thing could come out of <hi>Nazareth;</hi> whereas <hi>Nazareth</hi> ſignifies Separation, and Chriſt is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.26. to be Holy, harmleſs, ſeparate from Sinners; and therefore in the Myſterie of the name, he cometh a Prophet out of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> and ſo ariſeth a Prophet out of <hi>Galilee,</hi> which in the Myſterie of the name ſignifies a turning about, as aforeſaid; and therefore <hi>Nazareth</hi> is a City in <hi>Galilee;</hi> for <hi>Galilee</hi> in its Myſterie ſignifies turning about; <hi>Nazareth</hi> which ſignifies Separation, muſt be a City there; for Separation is the end and ſcope of turning about <hi>Acts</hi> 26. <hi>from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have made the large digreſſion aforeſaid; for that we think it correſpondent to our aim in every particular, which is to perſwade God fearing people to ſearch by Prayer and Meditation, whether (as we have before offered to conſideration) the greateſt part of Gods Holy writings, from the firſt of <hi>Gen.</hi> to the laſt of the <hi>Revel.</hi> are not to be looked upon, and enquired into as to be written for our learning of higher Myſteries than the letter holds forth unto us) which will be conſented unto by us, when the Lord opens our thoughts to conſider and apprehend, that they are moſtly by way of office, and as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives (as the two Mountains were, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.) of higher Myſteries to be owned and received by the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we return to offer to conſideration the Divine and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly reaſon, that the Holy God had in permitting the old Fathers recorded in the Old Teſtament, to have ſo many Wives; and to take Handmaids to their bed, and have ſo many Concubines; which was a kind of needfulneſs <hi>(conſider at is conſider and is)</hi> in reference to the fallen humanity, being fallen from God, whereby the true marriage with one Man and one Woman was broken off, which otherwiſe had never been, that the Man ſhould have had more Wives than one (as appears by <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.14, 15.) given him of God, for to beget of the ſame one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of fruit, or Children; and the reaſon is for that <hi>cauſa qua cauſa ſemper facit idem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence the many Wives came in through diſobedience, and figured forth, that when the Man fell away from that Heavenly Diety, he then begat with his Wife two ſorts of births of dfferent natures, by reaſon whereof, one killed the other, figured forth in <hi>Cain, Gen.</hi> 4.8. who killed his Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> the breath of God; and therefore if
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34694:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>if the revolt from God had not been committed, then the only Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage which God made in the beginning had not been broken; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had the Handmaids been needful to bring forth Children.</p>
            <p>But when the only God ſaw that his Marriage that he had made in Unity and Concord was broken off, and that from the Apoſtate and corrupt generation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here came forth always ſtrife and contention, figured forth by and in the ſtrugling in <hi>Rebeccahs</hi> womb, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.22, 23. which Gods pure and Holy Spirit could not endure that there ſhould be always ſtrife and diſſention in the humane being; and therefore he looked upon the Power and Omnipotency of his being and Spirit, for to beget thereout Miniſters and Servants (through his moſt great Wiſdom) to ſet up, and by degrees to re-eſtabliſh through their ſervice, the only Marriage again, by the begetting of Divine Children in a figure.</p>
            <p>To this end the Lord at firſt choſe <hi>Abraham</hi> for a Servant, and a Father, to make him fruitful as well Divinely as Humanely, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.9. Out of whoſe fruitfulneſs there was brought forth <hi>Iſaac, Jacob, David, Solomon, Moſes,</hi> and many others, in whom the manly being was in ſtrength to be ſerviceable to God.</p>
            <p>And this manly power (underſtand it Spiritually) ſaith the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> aforeſaid was inclined to generate; Now he could not generate without the help of a Female, that is, (ſaith the aforeſaid <hi>Germane</hi>) love to the fruitfulneſs of God, Truth, Comprehenſion, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which are all Feminine.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Women had yet Handmaids, by whom they were ſerved, and whom they might bring to their Husbands for to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by them.</p>
            <p>For they well knew that they ſhould not at firſt conceive by their Husbands, unleſs they laid (ſo the Deity ordered it,) their Handmaids (which are Faith, Hope, and Love, Gods obedience in figure) with their Husbands; otherwiſe they could not bring forth any Fruits (Spiritually) in the Humanity.</p>
            <p>Behold for this reaſon the Women laid a Handmaid with their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, to the end that he thereby ſhould ingender and beget increaſe or fruit, which is a ſerviceable work, whereby the earthly luſts are broken and deſtroyed.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:34694:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now for this end <hi>Sarah</hi> laid her Handmaid called <hi>Hagar</hi> by her Husband, (and ſhe is a growing and increaſing Woman coming out of affliction, for ſhe came out of <hi>Egypt</hi>) of her, <hi>Abraham</hi> begat an illegitimate Child, before <hi>Sarah</hi> can bring forth a legitimate Child. <hi>Hagars</hi> Child was named <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> and called <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>The Son of the Bondwoman,</hi> Hagar, <hi>aforeſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>Rachel</hi> the lawful Wife (for whom <hi>Jacob</hi> ſerved 7 years) had <hi>Leah,</hi> which is a Labrateſs, who was laid firſt with <hi>Jacob, Rachels</hi> Husband, with whom the Husband muſt firſt beget fruit, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.32. and her firſt born was <hi>Reuben,</hi> the Son of Sight, which is the firſt fruit to be brought forth, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.17, 18. <hi>To whom I ſend thee, to open their eyes, and to turn them from darkneſs to light,</hi> which was the firſt thing <hi>Ananias</hi> ſaid to <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 9.17, 18. <hi>Brother</hi> Saul <hi>receive th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſight.</hi> Then was brought forth (<hi>Gen.</hi> 29.33.) <hi>Simeon,</hi> Hearing, which is the next to Sight, and then <hi>Levi, ver.</hi> 34. one adjoyned; for after the Seeing and Hearing with the eyes and ears of their underſtandings, which the Apoſtle prays for in the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> behalf, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.18. then there is way made to be joyned (in a further preparation) with the Deity and Humanity. And then is born <hi>Judah,</hi> Confeſſion, in which God is owned, according to that <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.1. <hi>In</hi> Judah <hi>is God known or owned, his Name is great in</hi> Iſrael; that is, his Being is great in the prevailer, as the Angel interprets the name, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.28.</p>
            <p>Theſe therefore are the Adminiſtrations that go before in reference to the preparation, for the Deity and renewed Humanity to be joyned together, even as our Saviour ſet forth ſeveral Adminiſtrations (in reference to his own office to be done by him) under the names (in a Myſterie) of his Diſciples; as firſt, he aſſigns <hi>Simon,</hi> it notes obedience <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.2. For that the Sinner is firſt called to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is the obedience of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.5, 6, 26. And therefore is called <hi>Peter,</hi> that is, the Rock of Faith ſounded on the obedience. The next ſent forth is <hi>Andrew,</hi> which notes Virility or Strength, which is next to <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> the obedience of Faith, which brings forth the ſtrength, as appears <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. <hi>tot. cap.</hi> And we are commanded to be <hi>ſtrong in the Lord, Epheſ.</hi> 6.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hence called <hi>Simon Peter</hi>'s brother in the Myſterie. The next in his office is <hi>James,</hi> the ſame with <hi>Jacob,</hi> the ſubduer of the ſin, the next to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34694:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Andrew</hi> the ſtrength, for then able to overcome by wreſtling, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, and he is the Son of <hi>Zebedee</hi> endowed, or a good dowry, as <hi>Jacob</hi> had when he wreſtled and prevailed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.28.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe all this, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10.) <hi>is through Grace I laboured more than you all; yet not I, but the grace of God in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>John,</hi> the Grace of God is next, and is the Brother <hi>James</hi> ſent <hi>to Preach in the wilderneſs of</hi> Judea, <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.1. in that bewildred ſtate (after they come out of the houſe of Bondage) of the confuſed thoughts in the repenting Sinner, that leads him from one by-path to another.</p>
            <p>Hence God in great Mercy and care to the repenting Humanity, ſends <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, as the forerunner (to the thorow waſher the Chriſt of God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.27.) to waſh away the remaining de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements of Sin, firſt in the River of Judgment, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. and this <hi>John</hi> is the Son of <hi>Zacharias,</hi> the remembrance of the Lord, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.72. for the Lord remembred his oath, <hi>ver.</hi> 73.</p>
            <p>And his office was to <hi>prepare the way of the Lord,</hi> by pulling down the high Mountains, the high thoughts of carnal reaſon, <hi>to make ſtrait the crooked ways,</hi> the ſubtle windings and turnings of the carnal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as thoſe ſubtile <hi>Jews</hi> had, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.20, 21. <hi>the rough ways ſmooth,</hi> the boyſterous and rugged thoughts in the carnal reaſon, as were in <hi>Paul</hi> before his Converſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.20. &amp; <hi>Acts</hi> 16. in the Jailor. <hi>Then ſhall all fleſh ſee the Salvation of God, Luk</hi> 3.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.1.</p>
            <p>Hence we ſee how our Lord ſent forth his own Adminiſtrations in and by way of office, in reference to his own deſign.</p>
            <p>And therefore it need not ſeem ſtrange, that the Lord ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and order ſome things to be done (in an extraordinary way) by the Old Fathers, <hi>Abraham Iſaack, Jacob, David, Solomon,</hi> to take to themſelves ſo many Wives &amp; Handmaids, by whom they begat ſo many and divers Children, even to figure forth in a Myſterie; the breaking thereby the many Luſts by degrees in the yet unrenewed Humanity.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Abraham</hi> begat a Son of <hi>Hagar,</hi> as aforeſaid, called <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> to figure forth the Servantiſhip under the Law, which muſt be caſt out when <hi>Sarah</hi> the Belief, hath brought forth <hi>Iſaack</hi> the true Joy, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.25. then muſt <hi>Iſhmael</hi> be caſt out, for that he was the figure of the Servantſhip under the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.30.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34694:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>So that it appears, that <hi>Sarah</hi> her giving <hi>Hagar,</hi> was by way of of office, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Seed of the Servantſhip under the Law was firſt to be bego<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ten by <hi>Abrabam,</hi> to figure forth it to be firſt brought forth, before the freedomſhip which is in the Belief, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1, 2. The like is to be ſaid of the reſt, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence they are to be looked upon as Spiritual Wiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, Handmaids, Concubines in Gods deſign, though they were alſo creaturely Wives whom they laid with their Husbands, to bring forth Children in a Myſterie by them, and not to ſatisfy their Luſt thereby, as the carnal men of the world think, and thereby practice it; and juſtify them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſo doing, upon the Old Fathers having many Wives, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>But this cannot be owned in reaſon, that the Lord ſhould wink at this in ſuch Holy Men as the Old Fathers were; nor that the Lord did connive at it to repleniſh the World thereby the ſooner; For that God had rather begin the World anew as he did after the Flood, which was deſtroyed meerly for that cauſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6, 4, 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it's ſaid that the Lord ſought a Godly Seed, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.15. Therefore there could be no ſuch connivence from the Lord upon any ſuch account aforeſaid; neither would the Lord have ſuffered his Holy Prophets to have ſtuffed his Holy Scriptures with ſuch ſtories, to the giving a liberty to the Fleſh, and ſo to the corrupting of good manners, and bringing in an ungodly Seed.</p>
            <p>This cannot by ſober Men be yielded unto, for that the Scriptures are Spiritual, and have for their ſcope, Spiritual things and deſigns, for that God is a Spirit, and will be worſhipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in Spirit and Truth, <hi>John</hi> 4.23.</p>
            <p>Therefore if we look upon their Wives, as creatural Wives only in Gods deſign and aim, we erre and miſtake, not knowing the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures what they mean in their Myſterie, nor yet the Holineſs of God, who is ſaid (<hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13.) to be <hi>of purer eyes than to behold Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, theſe Husbands had more Concubines, which figured forth alſo by way of office, Miniſtring Spirits which move to and fro, and are alſo Feminine by whom the Husbands eſpecially were ſerved in the divided times, for they were no longer to continue but until the lawful Wife became pregnant by her lawful Husband, and then the Handmaids with the Concubines have performed Spiritually (and in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34694:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>their Myſtery) their Service to a Divine fruitfulneſs, as Handmaids.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of our Lord who calls her ſelf a Handmaid, (<hi>Luke</hi> 1.38.) was the laſt Handmaid, becauſe ſhe brought forth the Chriſt of God the Saviour, who is the end of the Law and Prophets, and of the Types and Figures; Therefore when he comes and is born in us out of <hi>Mary,</hi> that pure Virgin Doctrine, God ſaith, <hi>Caſt out the bondmaid with her Son, Gal.</hi> 4.27. as it was ſaid when <hi>Sarah</hi> the lawful Wife had brought forth <hi>Iſaack</hi> the Son of true joyfulneſs, then <hi>Sarah</hi> cauſed <hi>Abraham</hi> (<hi>Gen.</hi> 46.10) <hi>to Caſt out the bondwoman and her Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it's apparent that <hi>Sarah</hi> gave no more <hi>Hagar</hi> her Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid to her Husband.</p>
            <p>And when the Handmaid with her Son is caſt out, then God ſets up in his Chriſtly being the decayed Marriage in its former State and condition even as it was ordained of God at firſt; namely, one Man and one Woman inward in the Spirit (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.) and outward among the creatures, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5.</p>
            <p>He that will not in this laſt part of time be obedient to this Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Marriage in the one only being; but will chooſe falſe Marriages, and marry Wives and Concubines to the ſatisfying of his fleſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, becauſe they read the Old Fathers aforeſaid had many, (but in a Myſterie only, as aforeſaid) let him take heed, for ſuch an one will be judged in the ſight of God for a Whoremonger, and ſhall not, according to the Word of the Lord, have any portion in the Kingdom of Heaven, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10. for that they are miſtaken in the ground and motive of their practice of having many Wives and Concubines, becauſe the Old Fathers had many; but it was practiſed and allowed them upon another account aforeſaid, and not to ſatisfy their Carnal Luſts and deſires thereby.</p>
            <p>And as many miſtake the reaſon of Gods allowance to the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing great licentiouſneſs; ſo not a few miſtake the Apoſtles teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Gods loving <hi>Jacob,</hi> and hating <hi>Eſau,</hi> before they had done good or evil, whereby they ſeem to introduce great partiality in God, (to Gods great diſhonour) with whom there is no reſpect of perſons; and can there be more partiality appear then in this, to love ſome before, or without preconſidering they had done good, and hating others before (or without preconſidering) they had done evil.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:34694:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The miſchiefs theſe may introduce, <hi>(ex fine rei)</hi> are preſumptions in ſome upon their falſe perſwaſion to think themſelves beloved of God with love of acceptation, before they have done good perſonally, as God requires, ſo upon Gods hating <hi>Fſau</hi> before he had, or is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſidered to do evil perſonally; what can it evidence in God, if it were (as it is not) ſo, but higheſt ſeverity without Juſtice in Gods doing it? and then St. <hi>James</hi>'s teſtimony is not true, <hi>Mercy rejoyceth over Judgment, James</hi> 2.13. But ſeverity to ſome before they do evil perſonally, rejoyceth over Mercy; and what can it produce in ſuch as think upon their eternal ſtate, but diſtractions, doubts, and fears, yea deſperation it ſelf, as ſtories, and not a few witneſs ſo much?</p>
            <p>Therefore we aſſure our ſelves, that Gods loving and hating <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> before they had done good and evil, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared only by way of office, and as reſpective repreſentatives of two diſſinct beings under thoſe two names; for in <hi>Jacob</hi> the Breath of God is in him, and that God loves before it do perſonally good, becauſe it comes out from God; and <hi>Eſau</hi> ſignifyes the Earthly being, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God hates that before it have perſonally done evil, for it comes not forth of God; but God did not perſonally hate <hi>Eſau,</hi> nor did <hi>Eſau</hi> continue hatred to <hi>Jacob,</hi> for <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Eſau</hi> was perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally reconciled to <hi>Jacob,</hi> which ſhewed his good nature, by which the Apoſtle, (1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14, 15.) declares a <hi>paſſing from death to life;</hi> and where did <hi>Eſau</hi> perſonally do to <hi>Jacob,</hi> as is expreſſed, <hi>Obad. ver.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. or to any that were with him; and did not the Lord alſo promiſe many bleſſings perſonally to <hi>Eſau, Deut.</hi> 2.5. Now where are any bleſſings given by promiſes to any reprobates or wicked men, as ſuch? though it is granted, that God gives them many bleſſings, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. to lead them to repentance (but not by promiſe) upon the account aforeſaid, unleſs they repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. Therefore <hi>Eſau</hi> was not at his birth a reprobate perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and that upon the account of Gods bleſſing him, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence that (<hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11.) is meant of <hi>Eſau</hi> in his office only, and as a repreſentative of the earthly nature and old world, <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8, 9. which God hates before the ſaid <hi>Eſau</hi> had done evil perſonally; and ſo all that is ſpoken of <hi>Eſau,</hi> (<hi>Obad. ver.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13, 14.) is ſpoken of <hi>Eſau</hi> by way of office, and as a repreſentative of the earthly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that is, cruel againſt the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:34694:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And therefore it being ſo as not ſpoken of <hi>Eſau</hi> perſonally, there can be no abſolute reprobation and rejection demonſtratively proved from what is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. concerning <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> before they had done good or evil.</p>
            <p>Which very expreſſion demonſtrates it to be moſt contradictory to Gods Mercy and Juſtice, (his two ruling attributes) and alſo to his Decree to reward or puniſh all mankind according to their works, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. and it's ſaid, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.29. <hi>the man ſuffers only for his Sin. Rev.</hi> 2.17. yet God ſaith, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.32. that <hi>as he lives, he deſires not the dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h of a Sinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if that be true, that God reprobates any in Decree, before they are preconſidered to do evil, then the Lord loves <hi>(abſit blaſphemia dicto)</hi> their death, contrary to his ſaid aſſeveration or Oath, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.32. Further, none dare ſay that God doth actually punniſh before the Sin is committed, and can he paſs a Decree to reprobate <hi>Eſau</hi> perſonally, before his Sin be conſidered as preexiſtent? this is moſt illogical and irrational, for that then the Act is <hi>in exercito,</hi> before it hath its object conſidered in reference to it, <hi>ut verſatus circa ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Sin is declared in Holy Writ to be the only object of Gods anger, who <hi>hates Iniquity, and loves Righteouſneſs, Heb.</hi> 1.9.</p>
            <p>Hence that of loving <hi>Jacob,</hi> and hating of <hi>Eſau</hi> before they had done good or evil, cannot be meant perſonally of them, but only by way of office as they ſtood in Gods deſign, the repreſentatives of elect and reprobate, under the ſignifications of their reſpective names of <hi>Jacob</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſau,</hi> as aforeſaid; <hi>Jacob</hi> having the Breath and inſpiration of the Divine being in the renewed Humanity, to tread down Sin to a prevailing over it; and <hi>Eſau</hi> as the Earthly being brought forth in the fallen Humanity, to the perſecuting and rejecting the breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or inſpiration of the Divine being, which ſince the fall of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity is the youngeſt, and brought in to rule over the elder; that is, <hi>Eſau</hi> in Myſtery the Earthly beng, <hi>John</hi> 1.4.</p>
            <p>Thus we have offered to conſideration, now conducing it is to come to the true knowledge of the Scripture Myſterie, to make diligent ſearch into the Scriptures, and that with moſt humbe Prayers to the Lord to give us to underſtand whether the greateſt part of Holy Writ be not to be looked upon by the Lords own deſign, as to be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34694:30"/>ſpoken and delivered to us by way of office, and as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives and ſignificancies of other Myſteries, than the letter of the Scriptures hold forth literally unto us; for otherwiſe we ſhall be much put to it to make ſome Scriptures true; for where did <hi>Eſau</hi> perſonally ſerve <hi>Jacob?</hi> yet it's ſaid, <hi>the elder ſhall ſerve the younger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if ſome Scriptures be not to be underſtood by way of office; how barren and low in expre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and matter, do they ſeem to be in their ſenſe and ſcope? Yea ſome ridiculous <hi>(abſit blaſphemia dicto)</hi> as that of <hi>Jacob</hi> his cloathing of his Son in a party coloured Coat, as great perſonages have done their Naturaliſts, we heartil, wiſh that themſelves would behold their Naturaliſts Coat, (who are the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ones in great meaſure) and improve the ſpectation of it, to mind them to return to the end and ſcope of <hi>Joſephs</hi> party coloured Coat, which was to figure forth the various and divers virtues expreſſed, (and we exhorted unto) 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6. that the <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the growing to perfection is cloathed with, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14, 15.</p>
            <p>And ſome paſſages in the Books called the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> are ſmiled at, fit for nothing but <hi>(movere cachinum)</hi> to move laughter; as that of <hi>Tobit</hi> and his Dog attending on him.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Tobit</hi> in its name ſignifies Goodneſs, and what ſerviceable creature is there more ready to wait on his Maſter than the Dog is? and therefore is not the Dog the fitteſt document and repreſentative of the good will, which will always wait upon <hi>Tobit</hi> the goodneſs in the renewed Humanity? Hence in the Myſterie, and by way of office and good document, <hi>Tobit</hi> and his Dog are not ſo contemptible, but a moſt uſeful meditation.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Shingler</hi> in his <hi>Penteglotte</hi> intimates, that the Book of <hi>Tobit</hi> was written in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and moſt call that Book and others <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> becauſe not written in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> though in truth that is no reaſon, if leaſure would permit to argue it; but whether it be a reaſon yea or no, yet we think the trueſt reaſon for that thoſe divided Books are called <hi>Apocrypha</hi> is, becauſe their Myſteries (for want of Faith, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with Prayer to read them) are hid from us.</p>
            <p>It might ſeem as ſtrange to read of our Saviours mixing clay and ſpittle to open the blind mans eyes; if it were not underſtood to be by way of office and Myſterie, as it was; for carnal reaſon cannot but think that mode to be the ready way to have continued him blind;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34694:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>but <hi>the fooliſhneſs of God is wiſer than Men,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25. <hi>ver.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>And how ridiculous was it <hi>(abſit blaſphemia dicto)</hi> to carnal reaſon to ſee Chriſt riding upon an Aſs to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and garments ſpread under him, and all the People ſhouting with acclamations before him, and ſtrewing Palm-branches in the way, crying <hi>Hoſanna to the higheſt;</hi> this was ſtrange to the letter learned <hi>Jews;</hi> hence that was by way of office and good document of higher Myſteries</p>
            <p>If all were not appointed by deſign from God by way of office, and better Document in Myſterie than the blind reaſon can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, they had been betrer (pardon the expreſſion) left out; what is the reaſon why the carnal wits ſay, they can get as much good or more at a Play, than hearing a Sermon, which is or ſhould be a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon ſome portion (more or leſs) of the Scriptures, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for Doctrine, for correction to mend them that are too much lifted up in falſe perſwaſions of their ſafe being, to raiſe them up which are too much (though there are but few of them) caſt down in doubts and fears; and alſo profitable for Exhortation to virtue, and Dehortation from vice; this ſhould be the mode of a Sermon out of the pattern of healing words, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. which is the ſpeaking as of the Oracles of God. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.11. And as for the Predicant he muſt do it (ſaith the Apoſtle there) as of the ability which God giveth for the end there expreſſed; the original is more ſignificant, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the words properly and moſt fitly are as out of the ſtrength which the Lord then ſupplyes, for it is an old ſaying, <hi>Spiritus non ſemper tangit corda Prophetarum,</hi> Gods Spirit doth not always touch the hearts of the Prophets, as it did Chriſt, whereby he always ſpake as one having authority, and not as the Scribes, <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.27. Now whether one can get as much good at a Play to his betterment, and to the good life, that's the ſtate of the Caſe; they may ſpeak as good words as ſignificant to their purpoſe, and with as much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the ſenſible affections as the Predicant can do; but if that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Lord ſupplies (which comes forth from God) be abſent, that is the enquiry, if it be abſent, then it is not Gods Ordinance, <hi>ut finis cui;</hi> and ſo it paſſeth away as like water through a ſieve; one would have thought that <hi>Dives</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment uſed to <hi>Abraham</hi> had been a moſt prevalent one to warn his Brethren to amend their lives, by deſiring him to ſend one from the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34694:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>dead to tell them of his torments, who wanted now a drop of water to cool his tongue, that abuſed his plenty of the beſt Equors in his life time; but <hi>Abraham</hi> tells him they have <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets, yet <hi>Moſes</hi> was not then living for them to hear; But let us hear them, and if they hear not them, ſaith <hi>Abraham, neither will they be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded though one a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe again from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we ſee it verifyed among our ſelves of late; what hath the fore waſting Plague, the raging and violent Fire in this City, and the late War? what have theſe, we ſay, reformed the generality of the People? teſtify it that can; Hence that which <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid is moſt true, If they hear not <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, <hi>neither will they be perſwaded though one come from the dead again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this we have ſpoken, is to remove the empty pretence afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and to mind us of that, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. and when the world by wiſdom knew not God, it pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſs of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſave them that believe; and all this cannot be true out of the letter only, but it is and muſt be out of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>The truth is, if we come to be perſwaded that God deſigned moſt of his Holy Writings to be looked upon, and applyed or ſpoken to us for higher Myſteries than the natural Creation, we ſhould find more benefit by reading of them, than we have words, or time to expreſs; as for inſtance, if we look upon the 1. or 2. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> which treats of the Worlds and Mans Creation, to intend another Spiritual World alſo; and the new Creation ſpoken of 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. <hi>But we look for new Heavens and new Earth, according to his promiſe wherein dwells righteouſneſs;</hi> would it not raiſe up your thoughts above this imperial world?</p>
            <p>Secondly, By looking upon ſomething in the Scriptures beyond and under the letter; it would preſerve the Saints honour from that reproach which is caſt upon them by ſomething which the letter of the Scripture holde forth they did; as what <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> did in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference unto thoſe evils that the Scriptures relate in the letter they did; So what <hi>Abraham</hi> did in having a Child b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hagar</hi> the Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman; ſo <hi>Jacob</hi> in his reproach for his many Wives, which yet are not to be looked upon as creaturely Wives only, but in higher Myſterie; ſo <hi>Solomon</hi> as having ſo many Concubin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, which are not yet to be looked upon as creatural only, but in a Myſterie.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:34694:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Thirdly, It will make the Scripture true in every part of it, which otherwiſe in the bare letter cannot be made true; for where did <hi>Eſau</hi> the elder Brother ſerve <hi>Jacob</hi> his younger Brother in the letter, yet in a Spiritual conſideration he did?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It will make the whole Scripture (which was written for our learning) <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. or concern and inſtruction to all, which otherwiſe cannot in the letter of perſonal concerns to all, at all times, and all places.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, it would preſerve the Holy Scriptures from ſeeming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions in themſelves, that yet were deſigned by Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to be moſt true in the ſenſe the Holy Ghoſt ſpiritually intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to be conſidered; for inſtance, <hi>Judas Iſcariot</hi> was choſen by Chriſt knowingly; as all his Apoſtles beſides were, and he did, and would have verifyed his name true which way ſoever he had perſevered in, he being as choſen of Chriſt by way of office as other Diſciples were; for <hi>Iſcariot</hi> ſignifies a death and killing, and by betraying his Lord and Maſter he was a <hi>Judas Iſcariot</hi> indeed, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Murderer, for he murdered and killed the juſt One, <hi>James</hi> 4.6. and being himſelf an inſtrument to do it by others; But if he had continued in the obedient life to his Lord, he had been alſo a <hi>Judas Iſcariot,</hi> a profeſſed Son of murdering and killing, the wicked nature in him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf, and an inſtrument to help to do it in others; So that Chriſt choſe him by deſign and way of office, which he might have performed the beſt way through grace, as he did the worſt way through Satans temptation; and we believe moſt of the names of Men, and others in Scripture, are deſigned by God to have a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſcope and end in their nomination, as <hi>Cain</hi> which ſignifies a poſſeſſion, and ſo he was of the earthly wicked nature, by killing his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> that is, a Divine breathing (for <hi>Abel</hi> ſignifies the breath) of God, being in him; but if he had preſerved <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bel</hi> his Brother, as the Heavenly breathing of God in himſelf (as his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) he had ſtill been a Poſſeſſion, but then a Poſſeſſion of the ſaid Heavenly being to his growing up to eternal life, (and as a Divinely Spiritual <hi>Germane</hi> ſaith, the names of the 7 Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> (are to be conſidered by way of office) have a twofold and contrary ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy intended to be in them by the Lords own deſign; We will inſtance but in one for brevity ſake, <hi>Epheſus</hi> the firſt Commonalty
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34694:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>or Church, ſignifyes a Deſirableneſs; As the mans elicit act conſents to the Grace of God: ſo that <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which ſignifies Deſirableneſs to good, as the takes part with his Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> the Breath of God, which is in all men that come into the World, <hi>John</hi> 1.9.</p>
            <p>And alſo <hi>Epheſus</hi> ſignifies Deſirablene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to the evil, as he takes part with his Brother <hi>Cain</hi> within him, the wicked nature to be his Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>Hence the Scripture names are deſigned to be conſidered by way of office, and great documents in Myſteries, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>If the Holy writings were more ſtrictly looked upon, and owned to be for other Myſteries than the letter ſeems to expreſs, there would not have been ſuch doubts and conteſis about the ſenſe of the Scriptures, as there are among many men (yea underſtanding and learned men) rais'd as there are, nor yet againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> any more than againſt <hi>Infant-Circumciſion,</hi> for that they are born to be done by way of office and good document to others concerns more than their own; and <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> may be adminiſtred to as good purpoſe upon the account aforeſaid, as ever <hi>Circumciſion</hi> could be.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Simon Peter</hi> were owned, as our Saviour choſe him by way of office as he did, there would not have been ſuch Volumns written as there have been about <hi>Peter</hi>'s perſonal Supremacy, <hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> as being the chief and firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> For <hi>Peter</hi> is and muſt be the firſt Biſhop or Adminiſtration by way of office of all the reſt, becauſe he is in his name the Obedience of Faith, which is the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratum</hi> and foundation of all things, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.1. as the adjunct occupate that is converſant about them, in reference to his office, and no perſonal Supremacy can be derived from <hi>Peters,</hi> meerly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal reſpect to continue always Supreme in his perſon; for that our Saviour blames his Diſciples for ſeeking any ſuperiority over one another as perſonally relating to them, in reſpect of their meer perſons, that they are to be conſidered by way of office both in faithfulneſs and order.</p>
            <p>So that where ever the Obedience of Faith doth moſt appear by way of office, performed by Spiritual men in office; there <hi>Peter</hi>'s Supremacy appears, and is ſet up as well in one Chriſtian Nation and Government as in another, elſe how could the Lord remove the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34694:32"/>Churches Candleſtick out of its place, if the the abuſe of a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual office were not the provoking cauſe of it? as he doth threaten, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            <p>God is ſo far in love with Obedience of Faith, that <hi>every Nation</hi> (as the Scripture ſaith) <hi>that fears God, and worketh Righteouſneſs, is accepted of him;</hi> And therefore the Spiritual Supreme Governor of every Nation that works Righteouſneſs, doth as truly exerciſe in and under his own Government. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Supremacy, that is, he being firſt in the Obedience of Faith by way of office, as aforeſaid, as another Nation doth.</p>
            <p>The great conteſt about Tranſubſtantiation in the Lords Supper would ſoon vaniſh, if it were known in the Myſterie, and in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Chriſts Spiritual Body and Bloud, as appears by <hi>John</hi> 6.53. to 63. where our Saviour tells us, it's <hi>the Spirit that quickens, the Fleſh profits nothing;</hi> what Fleſh do you think that is that profits nothing? and what Fleſh muſt that be which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>ver.</hi> 54, 55, 56. <hi>Who ever eats of it hath eternal life: and he dwells in Chriſt, and Chriſt in him;</hi> which therefore muſt declare indeed, a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation of Chriſts Fleſh and Bloud, but not of bodily Fleſh, <hi>for that</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>profits nothing, ver.</hi> 63. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>Ye were not redeemed with corruptible things, as Silver and Gold from your vain converſation, but with the Bloud of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. And was not Chriſts Body and Bloud periſhable, for that it was ſpilt on the ground in his Crucifixion?</p>
            <p>Hence the Miracles pretended to be ſeen of Chriſts bodily Bloud and Fleſh in the Conſecrated Bread, to what purpoſe are they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and the People perſwaded to believe them, if the corporal Fleſh be that which Chriſt ſaith <hi>profiteth nothing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There hath been great endeavours and undertaking by ſome, to reconcile all divided and oppoſing perſwaſions to be united in the bonds of operative love to God and our Neighbour, for that our Saviour ſaith on thoſe two Commands <hi>hang all the Law and the Prophets;</hi> and therefore what ever doth not promote, but deſtroy the ſaid operative love to God and our Neighbour (as all divided perſwaſions and opinions do by perſevering in them,) is not worth the contending for; Yea thoſe perſwaſions are to be abhor'd, which attempt to promote themſelves by blood-ſhed, and the poyſoning
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34694:33"/>one another, <hi>For the wiſdom which is above is peaceable, Jam.</hi> 1.17. <hi>and the wiſdom from below is earthly and deviliſh, ver.</hi> 15. upon which the ſaid attempts are to be abhor'd, by which any divided perſwaſion ſets up it ſelf as religious.</p>
            <p>There hath been &amp; is the like conteſt about many Scripture ſenſes and meanings out of the letter, which ſeem to thwart and croſs one another; whereupon ſome take the ſenſe this way, and ſome take it that way, and ſo contend about the letter ſenſe and meaning; but if we did frequently look for ſomething further under the letter in reference to higher Myſteries, than the bare letter ſeems to hold out, we ſhould forbear the hot contentions that are about the letter ſenſe; when we might think that ſomething further is intended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the letter, which we at preſent apprehend not for want of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual eyes to ſee further than the letter; for the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. <hi>No man knoweth the things of God, but the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs to him, ver.</hi> 14. Yet the Scripture letter is not to be rejected, (that's not our meaning) but alſo to look for ſomthing further under the letter, which may be of greater uſe and concern to us, than that which the letter ſeems to hold out.</p>
            <p>We ſay again, that we do not reject the letter of the Scripture, for how could any Myſtery be demonſtrated but out of the Scripture teſtimonies? We ſee that the Apoſtle, and our Saviour himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed all gain-ſayers to their Doctrine, out of the written teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets; Therefore we reject not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture letter in his due place and ſcope, but we wiſh only that the Scripture in the letter were looked upon for the moſt part to contain in them more Spiritual concerns and higher Myſteries by way of office and repreſentative documents, than the bareletter holds out, as <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> as hath been before declared, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>If we do not look upon the Scriptures in many places of them, to intend higher Myſteries than the letter holds forth, then the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſpeech of the letter 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. may be often verifyed and made true, <hi>that the letter killeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It kill'd our Saviour, his Apoſtles, and the Prophets, <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.34, 35. and all the Martyrs ſince Chriſt and his Apoſtles fell aſleep.</p>
            <p>It's meerly the letter without looking further, for what the letter is intended for a further conſideration, to hold out ſomthing further
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34694:33"/>by way of office; that hath been the occaſion of much miſchief and wickedneſs, as poyſoning and blood ſheds by miſtaking the letter, as the literal indulgencies given to many for doing and promoting ſuch wickedneſs, as aforeſaid; whereby they are encouraged by hopes of pardon to do the greateſt wickedneſs they are put upon, which hopes ariſe from the ſaid indulgences offered unto them upon a verbal and outward confeſſion only; whereas the Scripture tells us, <hi>he that confeſseth and forſaketh his Sins ſhall have mercy, Prov.</hi> 28.13. <hi>and not every one that cryeth Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into his Kingdom, Matt.</hi> 7. Therefore God muſt needs hate all ſuch ways and means to promote Religion by ſuch like practiſes; for the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. <hi>We muſt not do evil, that good may come of it, whoſe damnation is juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence we muſt be ſure that we do not abuſe the Scripture, either in the letter or Myſterie of it, that may incite us to do any miſchief to others; for that is againſt the command, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which if we did believe thoſe <hi>mille machinationes, &amp; noſcendi artes,</hi> would ſoon be given over, as they did who uſed curious arts, <hi>burnt their Books in the ſight of men, Acts</hi> 19.19.</p>
            <p>We muſt take heed that we do not in the ſticking to the letter-ſenſe, hold forth out of that letter any thing that tends to the reproach of the high Saints of God, as that of <hi>Lot</hi> and his Daughters aforeſaid, what they are pretended to do; So of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> aforeſaid, of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s many Wives, and <hi>Solomon</hi>'s many Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines aforeſaid; and ſo the reſt of the Patriarchs.</p>
            <p>This muſt be granted without contradiction, that as the Lord created the Humanity innocent; ſo upon its Fall and Diſobedience, the whole intention and deſign was to magnify his great attributes of Mercy and Bounty to the ſaid fall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Humanity, by bringing it back again to its firſt innocent eſtate, but yet by ſuch ways and means as he in his infinite Wiſdom thought fit and advantageous thereunto; and thoſe ways and means he would not diſcover and lay open to all, but keep them to his own revealment to whom he pleaſes, as even to the Babes and teachable ones, and not to the wiſe and learned, and prophane men of the world, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Father I thank thee, becauſe that thou haſt hid theſe things from
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34694:34"/>the wiſe, and men of underſtanding, and haſt opened them unto Babes, Matt.</hi> 11.29.</p>
            <p>Hence it cannot be, but that the Lord did intend many other things under the letter, than the letter it ſelf doth expreſs; and alſo did intend other things to be acted and done, or not to be done, by way of office only, and not for their perſonal concerns at preſent who did them, as he bid <hi>Hoſea to take a Harlot to Wife, Hoſea</hi> 1. What! was the Lord ſo much pleaſed with ſuch a reception? ſurely not, ſince he abhors the practice of Whoremongers and Adulterers, but the Lord aſſigned that to him by way of office, as he repreſented the (for ſo his name ſignified a Saving) Lord himſelf by that ſaid office, even his willingneſs to take the Apoſtate adulterated Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity unto himſelf again, which is become an Harlot from him, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p>But the danger of what we have propoſed of looking beyond the bare letter, for ſome Myſterie under the ſaid letter, is the turning the Scripture into allegories, and ſo make the Scriptures a Noſe of wax, as is pretended by doing ſo, as aforeſaid; but do not they more truly turn them into a Noſe of wax, that in their reſpective religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions are as truly oppoſite diſparates, alike oppoſing one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in what they contend for; as a Lyon, a Bear, a Fox, and many other devouring creatures, are diſparates in their reſpective natures, one to another; for as the aforeſaid devouring creatures do alike op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe one another in their reſpective Nature all of them, as one doth to one; ſo are all the divided perſwaſions aforeſaid (we name none) oppoſite diſparates to all others as to one of them.</p>
            <p>And yet they all pretend their Scripture letter to juſtify them all reſpectively; which cannot be that it ſhould, for that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are from the Holy Spirit of God, and the Spirit is but one, and moves uniformably to one thing; and therefore if there be 13 divided perſwaſions, as religious ones, then 12 of them muſt be meer fictions, and not dictated by and from the Holy Spirit, but out of their own good thinkings; though every one pretends the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the ground of his perſwaſion, as once two great parties, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians,</hi> and their oppoſites, did both pretend to the Nine and Thirty Articles of the Church, to juſtify (though oppoſite to each other) their perſwaſions; whereupon King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. took occaſion to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34694:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſay, it was ſome ſatisfaction to him in reference to both the divided perſwaſions aforeſaid, that they did reſpectively flie to the Nine and Thirty Articles for what they held.</p>
            <p>Now do not theſe make the Scriptures a Noſe of wax, more truly than they do which are charg'd to do it? by turning the Scriptures into allegories, <hi>turpe eſt doctori cum culpa redarguit</hi> when the Kettle doth call the Pot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what are Parables? (which are ſpecifyed in the Scriptures) what are they but Allegories that contain other things and Myſteries than the letter holds forth? and <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.34. it's ſaid that Chriſt ſpake nothing to them without a Parable, and he had his end in it; to reſerve the Myſteries under the letter to his own revealment and diſcovering as he thought fit, and well knew who are fit to receive them, <hi>John</hi> 16.12. <hi>I have many things to ſay to you, but ye are not able to bear them now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſecondly, Our Saviour would not diſcover them to the wicked World, which were not worthy as yet to be taught by him, and would not uſe them aright, to the ends for which that under the letter is intended; Therefore he ſays to his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. <hi>Give not Holy things to Dogs, nor caſt Pearls before Swine;</hi> that is, thoſe Myſteries aforeſaid under the letter, to thoſe that are of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and ſnarling diſpoſitions, and of a ſwiniſh nature, that are upon all occaſions wallowing in the mire of this Word, and tread the ſaid Pearls under their feet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> ſaid to his Son, to whom he communicated and taught his ſecrets, <hi>My Son</hi> Tatt, <hi>hide theſe things from the wicked and prophane world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour never intended that proud and ſelf-willed men in their own eys, ſhould have his ſecrets revealed unto them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25, 26. <hi>I thank thee O Father, Lord of Heaven and Earth, becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them to Babes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that it's not the ſelf-wiſdom, nor great letter-learning that makes us capable of underſtanding the Myſteries contained in the Scriptures; but there muſt be humility, and innocency of life, to move the Lord to cauſe us to underſtand thoſe Myſteries, for that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34694:35"/>they are contained under the letter, which though the learned do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and ſee what it holds forth in its axiomatical diſpoſition, yet they can ſee no further than that; we well remember that Arch-Biſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Uſher</hi> Preaching in St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Cambridge</hi> upon the Text, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.24.25. which upon an occaſion of a Faſt kept when King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. was in <hi>Spain,</hi> and all the People ſighed, and longed for His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties return; He took his Bible and clapt his hands together, and ſaid in this manner, (turning himſelf to the Doctors, and Heads of the Univerſity there preſent) <hi>Well, you Doctors, you ſhall never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this Book, unleſs you lead Godly lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee that our Saviour ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 7.17. <hi>If any man do my Will, he ſhall know of the Doctrine, whether it be from Heaven, or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence, without the obedient life, our Saviour told the learned Scribes and Phariſees, they could not know the Doctrine, <hi>whether from Heaven, or no;</hi> for though learned men may and do judge of things within the compaſs of Reaſon, yet not of Heavenly things above it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. becauſe God reveals them by his Spirit, and tells us, (<hi>ver.</hi> 4.) <hi>the natural man recieves not the things of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, neither can he know them, becauſe they are Spiritually diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's a true rule, <hi>Quicquid recipitur, recipitur per modum reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientis,</hi> that is, whatſoever is received, is received according to the diſpoſition and temper of the receiver; as it appears by the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a diſtempered pallate, in reference to Meat and Drink; and therefore men cannot underſtand though never ſo learned, the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries contained in Scripture under the letter, unleſs they be Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually taſted and reliſhed by them.</p>
            <p>Hence St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, for the aſſurance of thoſe he wrote to, that he declared the very truth unto them, wherein they ſhould walk, Saying, <hi>that which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eys, which we have looked upon,</hi> (of the wore of life) <hi>declared we unto you, that ye alſo may have fellowſhip with us; and truly our fellowſhip, is with his Father, and with the Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 3.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour tells us, <hi>John</hi> 14.23. that the way to have that fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, is, to <hi>keep his Words;</hi> and then he ſaith, He and his Father <hi>will come to them, and make their abode with him,</hi> vid. <hi>ver.</hi> 21.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:34694:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>We ſay no more in reference to what we have ſaid concerning the adjuſting of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> by our <hi>New Diſcovery</hi> aforeſaid, than what we have ſufficiently declared, and ſet forth.</p>
            <p>Unleſs you be pleaſed to give us leave to offer our thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the mode or manner of Baptiſing thoſe which are to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in Baptiſmal water.</p>
            <p>We think, and are perſwaded in our ſelves, (but we do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it, <hi>ſed diſquiri relinquimus</hi>) that the Feet only of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized are only to be covered with the Baptiſmal water.</p>
            <p>Our reaſons are, firſt from Baptiſms operation and uſe, appointed by the Lord in a Myſterie, relating, and eſſentially depending on <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> which was ordained by God (before <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in its operation) for the cutting off the groſs Sins from the depraved Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity.</p>
            <p>And for that many defilements of Sin do for ſome time remain after the groſs Sins are cut off; therefore the Lord brought in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> and ordained it for to waſh away the remaining defilements of Sin, after the groſs Sins are cut off.</p>
            <p>And theſe defilements are remaining in the affections, chiefly to be purged and cleanſed away, according to that, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. <hi>Therefore having theſe promiſes, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, Epheſ.</hi> 5.27.</p>
            <p>Alſo the members of the body, which figure out the affections, are the Feet, <hi>à Simili,</hi> becauſe as the Feet carry the Body, ſo the affections carry the Soul here and there, whither predominancy and intereſt do lead or force them; hence <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Take heed to thy foot when thou goeſt to the houſe of God, and be more ready to hear, than to give the Sacrifice of fools,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hence the Feet only upon the account aforeſaid are to be covered with Baptiſmal water, from an induction of particulars. Firſt, For that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was ordained to waſh and cleanſe away the defilements of Sin, and thoſe defilements are in the affections, and the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are reſembled to the Feet.</p>
            <p>Hence we offer it to conſideration, whether the Feet (upon the account aforeſaid) be not to be covered with Baptiſmal water?</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:34694:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Our ſecond reaſon for it, is from Chriſts practice, only in waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Diſciples Feet, <hi>John</hi> 13.5, 6. Secondly, From his ſpeech to <hi>Peter,</hi> who denyed our Saviour out of ignorant modeſty, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility to waſh his face.</p>
            <p>But upon our Saviours replication to him, that if he did not waſh his Face, he had no part with him; <hi>Peter</hi> then rejoyns upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and ſaith to his Lord, <hi>if ſo, then not my feet only, but alſo my hands and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this our Saviour anſwers, to correct <hi>Peter</hi>'s (now ignorant forwardneſs) upon his (and our) Lords informing <hi>Peter</hi> concerning the waſhing of his Feet ſaying, he that is releaſed upon the account aforeſaid, needs not ſave to waſh his Feet, and is clean every whit.</p>
            <p>Our Saviours ſaid expreſs, <hi>ver.</hi> 10, is in the Original thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Where it is evident, that our Saviour uſeth theſe two words of divers ſignifications, yet our Tranſlators render them both in one, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to waſh, ſaying, <hi>he that is waſhed, needeth not ſave to waſh his Feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas the firſt word which our Saviour uſeth is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and differs much from the other word he uſeth, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Infinitive Mood.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a Participle Paſſive of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that comes of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to looſe, or to be releaſed from ſomething needful to be releaſed from, which releaſment (we are perſwaded) in our Saviours meaning and intention, is that which relates to <hi>Circumciſions</hi> releaſment, which performs in the Myſterie the foregoing work in the repenting Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, by cutting off the groſs Sins, as aforeſaid; which muſt be done, before <hi>Baptiſms</hi> work in its Myſterie doth take place, for to waſh away the remaining defilements, when <hi>Circumciſion</hi> hath cut off the groſs Sins aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Then the repenting Humanity is ſurely releaſed from his great bondage, according to that expreſs, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.16. <hi>And ought not this Woman</hi> (being a Daughter of <hi>Abraham</hi>) <hi>whom Satan hath bound, Lo, this Eighteen years to be looſed from this bond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word out Saviour uſeth here to be looſed, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive Mood of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a Participle of it, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:34694:36"/>
            <p>Hence our Saviours meaning in the ſaid Verſe, was to inform <hi>Peter</hi> of ſo much, by uſing the Participle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which notes releaſed, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>He that is releaſed <hi>(viz.)</hi> by <hi>Circumciſions</hi> work) needs not ſave to waſh his Feet, which are his affections, figured forth by the Feet, upon the account aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And therefore our Saviour ariſeth from his Paſchal Supper, and powr water, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, into waſhing Veſſels, alluding to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> veſſels, they uſed (if not the ſame) for their daily waſhing, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.2, 3, 4, 5 <hi>to waſh his Diſciples Feet,</hi> and he comes to <hi>Simon Peter</hi> to waſh his Feet, and it's likely firſt to him, becauſe under the ſame Figure of his two names, he is the firſt of Chriſts Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations to be, and was ſent forth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.2.</p>
            <p>Now ſince our Saviour waſhed the Feet only, upon this account aforeſaid; We offer it to conſideration, whether the Feet only, in reference to <hi>Baptiſms</hi> work in its Myſterie, and the order of it, are not to be covered, and not the whole Body to be plunged in Baptiſmal water, and that from the words of Chriſt to <hi>Peter,</hi> Ver. 10. He that is releaſed, as aforeſaid, needeth not ſave to waſh his Feet, not his hands and head alſo; for that by our Saviours diſcourſe to <hi>Peter,</hi> they are not the object of <hi>Baptiſms,</hi> but <hi>Circumciſions</hi> work in its Myſterie, which cuts off the groſs Sins, which are of two ſorts; Firſt, open Prophaneſs and wickedneſs, figured forth by the Hands, which are the inſtruments of outward practiſes in ſome reſpect or other, whether good or evil.</p>
            <p>Now the ſecond ſort, are thoſe which lie in the Head, the ſeat of carnal reaſon, which are the choſen Holineſſes thereof.</p>
            <p>In both theſe our Saviour lies buryed; Hence it's ſaid, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.9. <hi>He made his grave with the wicked, and with the rich in his death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the letter, Chriſt was buryed alone, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.60. <hi>And</hi> Joſeph <hi>laid him in his own new tomb, which he had hewn out of the Rock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it's apparent, that Chriſt lies buryed alſo in the wicked, and in the rich as long as they continue ſo; though he was but once buryed, and alone in <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s ſaid new Tomb. Now as the wicked are the prophane ones, ſo the rich are ſuch, which are rich in their
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34694:37"/>choſen Holineſſes, as the Apoſtle doth atteſt it of the <hi>Corin.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Now ye are full, now ye are rich,</hi> that is, in their ſelf know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and choſen holineſs, as appears, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. to <hi>ver.</hi> 8. So was the Lawyer that politique queſtioniſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.20, 21. <hi>All theſe have I kept from my youth, what lack I yet?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 9.40. The Phariſees ſaid, <hi>are We blind alſo?</hi> Hence Chriſt tells them, <hi>ver.</hi> 21.38. That Publicans and Harlots go to the Kingdom of God before them, becauſe it's eaſier to convince theſe, for that their groſs Sins ſtare them in the face, when yet the other ſort do juſtify themſelves, as he did, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.20. Therefore when Chriſts Diſciples were releaſed from the groſs Sins of Hand and Head, (as they were) other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they could not have been his coming on Diſciples; then our Saviour might ſay to them, He that is releaſed, as aboveſaid, need not ſave to waſh his Feet.</p>
            <p>Hence we ask again, <hi>ex vi praedict.</hi> whether it be not more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentaneous to <hi>Baptiſms</hi> work in a Myſterie, which is the waſhing of the affections, to cover the Feet only in Baptiſmal water.</p>
            <p>And it's obſervable, that when the Eunuch was Baptized by <hi>Philip, Acts</hi> 8.38. It's only ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, They both deſcended into the water; and then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> when <hi>Philip</hi> had Baptized him.</p>
            <p>Both which diſtinct acts of their deſcending into the water, and their aſcending out of the water again, do hold out no more in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the ſaid Acts themſelves, but to the covering of the Feet only in water, not covering the whole Body in water, as if that were the proper and peculiar ſignificant, relating to a burying with Chriſt in <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which burying comes when the Circumciſed in a Myſterie, and alſo the Baptized in a Myſterie, (that is, Spiritually waſhed from all the remaining defilements of Sin, which are a true buryal, and the laſt degree of the three ſpecifyed in reference to Chriſt, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed, Dead, and Buryed; and then follows the Reſurrection again to a new life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.5.</p>
            <p>Hence nothing can be extorted out of the ſaid expreſs of burying with Chriſt by <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> to pretend to a covering of the Baptized all over in Baptiſmal water, but the covering of the Feet only with
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34694:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>water, is moſt agreeable to Chriſt's practice in waſhing his Diſciples Feet.</p>
            <p>This we have offered to conſideration, and do not determine it: neither will we be contentious in the caſe, <hi>ſed relinquimus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerving the Apoſtles rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. <hi>If any man luſt to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtom, neither the Churches of God;</hi> for that is of more evil conſequence, than the doing or forbearing of a Ceremony, which is but a concomitant for a preſervative of a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificancy of ſome particular thing, that hath its uſe in uſhering in (in due order and place) the two great Commandments, upon the which our Saviour told the Lawyer, did hang all the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            <p>Hence to break the operative love to God, and our Neighbour; for the not doing, or doing any relative Ceremony, is, to ſet up the Ceremony above the performing of the two ſaid great Commands in their end and ſcope.</p>
            <p>And whether he that doth ſo, doth not hinder all the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances in reference thereunto; for that St. <hi>James</hi> declares, 2.10. <hi>He that fails in one point, is guilty of all,</hi> for all makes up but one rule of love, which is broken by oppoſition; becauſe doing, or not doing a Ceremony, upon which contention do proceed many horrid miſchiefs and miſeries, as are ſeen by woful experience.</p>
            <p>Hence the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We have no ſuch cuſtom, neither the Churches of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's not unworthy of our conſideration, of the Ceremony menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 11.3. where he ſets forth, with the grounds on which it is founded in its acts reſpectively, to be done by Men and Women Believers, with all the concomitants relating to the ſaid Ceremony, and the reaſons expreſſed and laid out, from <hi>ver.</hi> 4, 5. to <hi>ver.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Yet when the Apoſtle had ſo fully argued for it in all the reſpects, as aforeſaid; He would not contend for it, to the breach of love and peace among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> but ſaith <hi>ver.</hi> 16. <hi>If any luſt to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtom, neither the Churches of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:34694:38"/>
            <p>What Ceremony is there in all the Apoſtles writings, ſo largely expreſſed and urged for practice, upon ſo many reaſons and induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as that aforeſaid? yet is it not ſo much as taken notice of at this day for any practice, though it ſtand Recorded in Holy Writ ſo fully, as aforeſaid; when as yet ſome Ceremonies are contended for with great Zeal, <hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> as if they were the marrow and life of our Religious Services, needfully to be obſerved, (as they thought of <hi>Circumciſion, Acts</hi> 15.1.) or we cannot be ſaved; yet is there no particular expreſs for the Ceremony, which ſometimes we pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, but is taken up meerly upon an alluſion to a word or two in Holy Writ, upon which account we only practice the ſaid Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, as we do for covering all over the perſons to be Baptized in Baptiſmal water, becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Being buryed with him in Baptiſm;</hi> therefore by reaſon of the ſaid expreſs, it's greatly contended for, to cover all over the perſon that is to be Baptized in Baptiſmal water.</p>
            <p>And what contentions have there been, and ſtill are, againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm?</hi> becauſe there is no expreſs Command for it, when it's no where forbidden, which ſurely God would have done, if he had diſowned it upon the account aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo as good a document and inſtruction by way of office adminiſtred, as ever <hi>Circumciſion</hi> could be upon the like account aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Hence St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s reflexion upon the <hi>Galathians,</hi> contending only for the Ceremony of <hi>Circumciſion, Gal.</hi> 3.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>O unconſidering</hi> Galathians, <hi>who hath bewitched you?</hi> may be ſaid of Us,
<q>
                  <l>—teneros quis mihi faſcinat agnos?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who doth ſeduce our filly Sheep?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And them from ſtraying doth not keep?</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>By contending about doing, and not doing of ſome Ceremonies, meerly upon an uncertain directive of us in the caſes aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Thus verifying what the Poet ſays,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>The ſubſtance we as Nifles take,</l>
                  <l>And Nifles for our work we make.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:34694:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This is moſt true (it's fear'd) in our conteſts aforeſaid; but let us for the time to come deſiſt, and contend for the Faith (by a quiet and peaceable life in all love) which was once delivered to the Saints, <hi>Jude</hi> ver. 3. and not for the doing or forbearing a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, the ſubſtance whereof is the operative love to God and our Neighbour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.40. Let us not for the time to come con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any more againſt <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> than againſt <hi>Infant-Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion,</hi> ſince <hi>Infant Circumciſion</hi> was done, though commanded (as it was then needful) by way of office only, and <hi>Infant-Baptiſm</hi> may be done alſo by way of office, and to as good uſe and document, (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not forbidden) as ever <hi>Infant-Circumciſion</hi> was or could be.</p>
            <p>Neither let us be diſwaded from the allegorized ſenſe of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture on the pretence that ſome make it (as 'tis ſaid) a Noſe of wax, for we have already hinted how all divided perſwaſions do, that more frequently and ſtrangely than they which allegorize the Scriptures, which is done to raiſe up our thoughts above the letter.</p>
            <p>Only let us be ſure to take the Apoſtles advice, and keep the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of wholſom words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is the exemplar of healing words what is amiſs in us.</p>
            <p>And be careful to offer nothing as a higher concern (than the letter holds forth) but what is of a Spiritual document and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And what will then be the detriment or wrong to the ſaid portion of Scripture, or to our ſelves, by offering ſomething of higher Myſteries contained under the letter, than the letter holds forth.</p>
            <p>Surely this will incite us to read the Scriptures more and more, and preferr the reading of them (both for frequency and diligence) before <hi>Plutarchs</hi> Lives, the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Hiſtory, or any other Humane Hiſtory extant, what ever.</p>
            <p>Not that we ſhould reject the readng of theſe in their due time and place; For God hath given the Humanity a twoofold life and ſtate, to be converſant in. The Natural, and the Spiritual, yet not <hi>pari modò &amp; gradis,</hi> but ſubordinate, to be converſant in them, and not collateral, as if both were of like concern to us, though moſt make the Natural eſtate of more concern to us, than the Spiritual;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34694:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>Notwithſtanding our Saviour bids us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33. <hi>to ſeek firſt the Kingdom of God, and his righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We ſhould do in our converſe and reading of Divine and Humane Hiſtories, as our Saviour told the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> they ſhould do in their petty tithings, and the greater things of the Law; as <hi>Judgement,</hi> and the <hi>Love of God,</hi> theſe ought ye to have done, and not leave the other undone, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42.</p>
            <p>We ſhould read the Humane ſtories, to underſtand and obſerve how ſome ingenies and witts have improved themſelves in the ſtate and affairs of the habitable World, that we may imitate them, and do the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ut nobis honori amicis utilitati &amp; Reipublicae emolumento eſſe poſſimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Profitable to our Generation in reference thereunto.</p>
            <p>And let us read intermixt Hiſtories betwixt Civil and Inhumane writings, (not prophance writings, for it's ſaid, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.3, 4, 5. Let it not be once named amongſt you as becometh Saints.)</p>
            <p>Let us (we ſay) read the foreſaid, that we may underſtand and obſerve the various and manifold Serpentine ſubtileties, and what not Inhumanities, that vitious men have abounded in, wherein they have exerciſed themſelves like Lyons, Beats, and Tygers, and that againſt the Lords innocent ones, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11, 34, 35, 36. as if they came for no other end into this habitable world, <hi>but to bite and devour, and to be devoured one of another, Gal.</hi> 5.15.</p>
            <p>Theſe we may read to lament ſuch woful effects and practiſes as are ſeen daily to ariſe and iſſue forth from the degenerate and apoſtate humanity, fallen by diſobedience from its God.</p>
            <p>But we ſhould read the Divine writings with diligence and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency, and with humble Prayer to Almighty God, that in them we may come to know how and by what means the Lord will, and doth bring back the repenting humanity to the Heavenly life and ſtate again, in ſuch a way, and by ſuch means as the Scriptures do contain in them, under ſuch coverts and figures as the diſobedient perſevering humanity in diſobedience, ſhall never comprehend in the letter of of the Scriptures (though <hi>all Scripture is written for our learning</hi>) until we are taught of God, <hi>John</hi> 6.45. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34694:39"/>it is ſaid, that Chriſt ſpake to the Multitude in Parables, and without a Parable he ſpake not unto them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.34. but he explained them apart to his Diſciples, which Parables are no other but Allegories, which is the expreſſing of one thing to intend thereby another meaning, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24.</p>
            <p>There is a Noble Perſon in <hi>France,</hi> who hath (as it is reported) written of late a Book in defence of Allegories, and ſhewing the neceſſity of our owning of them to be moſt frequently in Scripture, if we expect to underſtand the Scriptures in their Latitude, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſtrange and high Myſteries which are wrapped up under the letter; yea, of more ſtrange, and high, and advantagious Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, than all the humane Stories can produce, or parallel.</p>
            <p>As for inſtance, that of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Conqueſt over 4 Kings, which had overcome 5 before, and only with 318 Servants born in his Houſe, and by theſe brought back the goods of the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and alſo his Brother <hi>Lot</hi> and his goods, and the Women alſo, and the People taken Captives by the ſaid Kings, <hi>vide Gen.</hi> 14.13, 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Maſter of a Family can, (in any Humane Story) be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced? who with them born in his Houſe to the number of 318, did overcome 4 Kings, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, and bring back the ſpoil again to them, from whom it was taken?</p>
            <p>Where do you read in Humane Story, of throwing down City walls by ſounding of a Trumpet, that the Conquerers might enter in? Yet we read <hi>Joſhua</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. of the walls of <hi>Jericho,</hi> thrown down with the blowing of Rams horns, whereby the Conquerers entred in.</p>
            <p>How ridiculous is that Story <hi>(abſit blaſphemia dicto)</hi> if no Myſtery were hidden under the letter for our learning; What do any in this habitable World expect to do the like, and ſo to gain an eaſy ent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance into their Enemies Cities? or do any one Family of 318. ever expect to overcome their Potent Enemies, conſiſting of 4 Kings in battle againſt them, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did? ſure no.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. Whatever is written, <hi>is writtten for our learning;</hi> Therefore every thing written, is for the learning and benefit of all Mankind reſpectively; yet this is not true (with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34694:40"/>reverence be it ſpoken) that all the Saints of God have actual bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of all what is written at all times, and in every place; which ſurely in a Scripture ſenſe and Myſtery, they may have at all times, and in every place, which yet in the letter expreſs only, they have not, nor have need of at all times, and in all places.</p>
            <p>As for Inſtance, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. <hi>All</hi> (not ſome) <hi>that will live Godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution;</hi> Now that's not univerſally true in the bare letter, but in a ſenſe under the letter, it's alwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s true of all the Saints of God, poor or rich, high and low, but not in the letter; for it's poſſible a man may live in a Wilderneſs alone, yea with his friends alſo, and in the midſt of his Potent friends, to defend him from all violence and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whatever, how ſhall theſe then ſuffer perſecution under them upon the account aforeſaid?</p>
            <p>But in a ſenſe hid under the letter it's always true, and cannot be otherwiſe, as the Apoſtle intimates, <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.29. Where he ſaith, he that was born after the Fleſh, perſecuted him that was born of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>This perſecuter, which is the Bondwomans Seed, is within us in all places, and at all times, and in all conditions, until caſt out by the Spirit of the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. Therefore in this ſenſe and no other, it's true of all, that <hi>live Godly in Jeſus Chriſt, they ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall we tell you of <hi>David</hi>'s Worthies? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.9, to 17. and what they did, and yet how uſeleſs that Story is to us, unleſs to gaze upon, if we take the Story but in the letter only?</p>
            <p>Alſo of what concern to us is <hi>David</hi>'s Conqueſt over <hi>Goliah?</hi> wherein the diſparity of ſtrength betwixt them is to be conſidered, the diſparity of <hi>David</hi>'s age and his, and the ſtrange means that <hi>David</hi> overcame him with, and all expreſt in the letter, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>How ſtrange and incredible is this to carnal reaſon? and to what purpoſe is it recorded in the Holy Bible, if nothing under the letter were contained, and of univerſal concern to all?</p>
            <p>And who would think that true of <hi>Moſes, Hebr.</hi> 11.23, 24, 25. in refuſing a Kingdom, and that a large one, offered to him for an Inheritance? or would not <hi>Moſes</hi> be taken by the ambitious Men of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34694:40"/>this world to be manifeſtly guilty of great folly in refuſing it, if ſomething better and higher Myſterie, were not meant there under the letter, for <hi>Moſes</hi> and others to enjoy above that Kingdoms in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</p>
            <p>What Magnanimity was there in thoſe mentioned for doing and ſuffering, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.33. to 38. <hi>cui bono?</hi> and to what purpoſe in reference to us? if it did not relate to, and concern all the Saints of God to do and ſuffer the like reſpectively, as they did aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And our Saviour ſaith of his Worthies, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.12. <hi>He that believes in me, the works that I do, ſhall he do alſo, and greater than theſe;</hi> Hence, there muſt be other things contained under the letter, than are held forth only in the letter.</p>
            <p>Otherwiſe the Scriptures muſt be in ſome things untrue <hi>(abſit blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemia dicto)</hi> in ſome things of no concern to our Heavenly eſtate) in ſome things ridiculous, and not worthy of taking notice of the reſpective Stories and Narratives in them, unleſs ſome higher My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries be hid under the letter, for us to enquire into; Therefore it muſt be granted, in reference to the letter, that ſome further thing muſt be intended under it, to remove all thoſe inſufferable incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies aforeſaid from the Scriptures, which otherwiſe muſt remain, and likewiſe to introduce all things in the right ſenſe (open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) in the Scriptures from under the letter, for to make the man of God <hi>perfect to every good work,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Tim. 2.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<bibl>
                     <hi>1 Theſ. 5.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>Conſider what we ſay, and the Lord give you Underſtanding to try all things, and to keep the beſt.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:34694:41"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>COurteous Reader, We beg thy pardon that ſo many <hi>Crypſes</hi> of defects, redundancies, and inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of parts, appear diſperſed here and there in this our <hi>Breviat</hi> of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm,</hi> adjuſted by our <hi>New Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this offence we beg thy pardon, becauſe it came not through remiſneſs and careleſneſs, but through many other cauſes, <hi>quas nunc praeſcribere longum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it being ſo, (as 'tis well known it is,) We hope thy Charity, according to Scripture requiring, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. in thy candid breaſt, will cover our errours aforeſaid committed.</p>
            <q>Qui non eſt ſponte nocens, is poene innocens ſit.</q>
            <p>And to make thee amends what we can, We have (by the labour of a very ready and good friend) inſcribed all and every one of them in the reſpective Margins, where they are our blemiſh.</p>
            <p>To remove thy trouble in poring upon an <hi>Errata,</hi> to find our meaning, what it ought to be there reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <q>Sic habetis confitentam reum &amp; avidum Lectori Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dato (quoad vires) ſatisfacere.</q>
            <q>Parcas igitur (ut poſſis) <hi>Parkero</hi> tuo, retineaſque illum, in favore tuo, dum manet lacheſi quod torqueat in <hi>Parkero</hi> parcendo, propter Confeſ. praedict.</q>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34694:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
